<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure sermons vpon seuerall partes of scripture, preached by George Gyffard, preacher of the worde, at Maudlin in Essex</title>
            <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852906</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852906</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 510:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure sermons vpon seuerall partes of scripture, preached by George Gyffard, preacher of the worde, at Maudlin in Essex</title>
                  <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 145 [i.e. 135], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Iudson, for Tobie Cooke, and Robert Walker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Four sermons, each with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Many pages misnumbered.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  1 Timothy VI, 17-19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John V, 7-13 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XII, 16-17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans VI, 1-14 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>FOVRE</hi> SERMONS VPON SEVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall partes of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Preached by GEORGE GYFFARD, <hi>Preacher of the worde, at Mauldin</hi> in Eſſex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by Thomas Iudſon, for <hi>Tobie Cooke,</hi> and <hi>Robert Walker.</hi> 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:2"/>
            <head>The Textes of the foure Sermons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>THE FIRST SERMON</label> 
                  <hi>1. Tim. 6. Chap. ver. 17.18.19:</hi> Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high minded, and that they truſt not in vncertaine ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but in the liuing God (which giueth vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly all thinges to inioye,) &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>THE SECOND SERMON.</label> 
                  <hi>1. Ioh. chap. 5. ver. 7.8.9.10.11.12.13.</hi> For there are three which beare record in heauen, the Father, the worde, and the holy ghoſt, and theſe three are one, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>THE THIRD SERMON.</label> 
                  <hi>Hebrewes 12. ver. 16.17.</hi> Let there be no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator or prophane perſon, as Eſawe, which for one portion of meate ſolde his birthright, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>THE FOVRTH SERMON.</label> 
                  <hi>Rom. 6. ver. 1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11:12.13.14.</hi> What ſhall we ſaye then? ſhall we continue ſtill in ſin that grace may abound? God forbid, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT worſhipfull Maſter Edward <hi>Lewkenor eſquire, one of her</hi> Maieſties Iuſtices of the peace in the countie of Suff. and to the right vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>and chriſtian Gentlewoman, Miſtris</hi> Suſan Lewken or his wife, grace with all aboundant bleſsings of this life, and the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He complaint of many both learned and verie godlie perſons, that the Church is burthened and inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with too great a multitude of bookes, is not made without cauſe, being grounded vpon the moſt holy worde of God, as alſo confirmed by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in that
<pb facs="tcp:18261:3"/> good houres are vnprofitablie ſpent, pietie with true holynes not a little hindred and impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Howbeit, it ſeemeth rather to be directed againſt vaine fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous and trifling pamphlets, wherein lewde and ignorante perſons haue onely taſte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, but eſpecially againſt mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous inuentions, vncleane and impure writings, which doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and defile, both doctrine &amp; manors (thereby deſeruing as a moſt contagious and peſtilent ayre to be conſumed and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with fire from amongſt the people of God) and not againſt
<pb facs="tcp:18261:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the wiſe and learned trauailes of godly men, whoſe whole pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and indeuour, is to profite the Church, and to further the knowledge and religion of the Lorde. For varietie of good and profitable bookes, ſeemeth to be neceſſarie (and therefore would not be wanting) both for the increaſe of knowledge and learning, becauſe one man, or a fewe, ſee not all thinges, as alſo for that euery man writeth not in one forme and maner, and therefore cannot anſwere the capaſitie of euerie one, for ſome fitte themſelues ſor ſmale and
<pb facs="tcp:18261:4"/> meane capacities, and ſome for learned and great vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Beſides, one hath neede of one ſpeciall inſtruction, and one of another, this man deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in one comforte and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die againſt his temptation, and an other in that which beſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth his infirmitie. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Sathan hath daylie newe deuiſes to aſſaile the faith of Gods elect, and to drawe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne neuer heard of before, which the Lorde by his ſpirite doth not onely reueale to ſome of his ſeruants aboue others, but
<pb facs="tcp:18261:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> prouideth remedies according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, which becauſe they cannot be miniſtred alwayes by worde of mouth; they are to be made knowne by writing to them that ſtand in neede. And ſurely the bountie &amp; riches of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie are ſo large, and his care of mans ſaluation and happines ſo great, that euen as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided variety of creatures for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans taſt, and vſe: ſo hath he prouided varietie of ſpiritual graces, for euery mans benefite &amp; delight, to the end that euery man might profit with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18261:5"/> pleaſure, or elſe be left without all excuſe. The conſideration of which reaſons, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>(Right worſhipfull)</hi> cauſed me, after I had obtained at the handes of that worthie Miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Gyffard,</hi> theſe fewe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, whereof he is the Author, to publiſh them in print to the view of the world. Not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in reſpecting ſo much mine owne gaine and commoditie, as the good and benefite of the Church of God. Whereof J conceiue no little hope, both by reaſon of the fruite and benifite which haue
<pb facs="tcp:18261:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to the comfort of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by his former workes, as alſo for the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the doctrine conteined herein, the which I rather commit to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the learned, and wiſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reader, then to commend them my ſelfe, leaſt in prayſing them for want of iudgement &amp; wiſedome, J ſhould in ſtead of beautie, bring diſgrace vpon them. Whatſoeuer they be, J thought it meete to Dedicate them to your worſhippes, moued thereto with many reſpectes. And firſt of all, that J might publikely teſtifie my dutie and
<pb facs="tcp:18261:6"/> thankefull heart, for your great kindenes and manifold courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies beſtowed, not only vpon me, but vpon them that are as neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly linked vnto me as my ſelfe. Of the which, if I ſhould be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull, J were worthie of the reward which the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> appointed for vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſons. But eſpeciallie the great accompt and honour that you haue obtained in the hearts of many of the beſt and wiſeſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for your ſingular god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines &amp; rare Chriſtian vertues, do turne mine eyes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vpon you, as comfortahle
<pb facs="tcp:18261:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> lightes ſhining in the midſt of this crooked generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as liuely examples to your brethren, and worthie orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Goſpel. And J haue ioyned you together in this dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only for the neer band wherewith you are ſo nighly ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together in mariage, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for that you do not only ſtriue together in one courſe to obteine the high price of your calling, and that euerlaſting crowne of glory reſerued for you in the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens, but alſo for that you are mutual helpers one to another to the performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:18261:7"/> duties, but ſpeciallie in the wel gouerning and trayning vp of your houſholde, which thereby as a fruite of your rare and holy labours the Lord hath ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as that the heauenly eſtate &amp; behauiour thereof, may be a preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to many families, if it would pleaſe the Lorde to giue them heartes to confirme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thereunto. But I ceaſe to ſay ſo much as I knowe, leaſt in ſpeaking the truth, might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure enuie, and ſeeme to flatter you, whoe of all other haue leaſt delight in that veine. The onlie thing which I ought in dutie, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18261:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> may ſafely do, is firſt to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, that he would ſaue &amp; preſerue you, &amp; yours, from the manifolde ſubtilties of Sathan, and the dangerous baites &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of this world, and to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the good work that he hath begunne in you vnto the day of Ieſus Chriſt. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to requeſt you, that you would take in good parte this ſimple gifte that J offer vnto you, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting all thinges, both in regarde of it, and my ſelfe, in the beſt parte, and with that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection J offer it to you. And thus once againe, beſeeching al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie
<pb facs="tcp:18261:8"/> God to bleſſe and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue you many happie yeeres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your owne comfort, and the goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Church, as alſo to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable vnto the holy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, which hath many yeeres continued in your congregation, in which, in my childhood I was trained vp in the firſt principles of Chriſtian religion, the ioyful remembrance of which benefit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I truſt ſhall neuer departe from me, either in life, or death. J in all duetie and humble man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robert Walker.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>6. Decemb. 1598.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Timoth. 6. Chapt.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>17</bibl> Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rge them that are rich in this world that they be not high minded, and that they truſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vncertaine riches, but in the liuing God (which giueth vs abundantlie all things to inioy)</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>18</bibl> That they do good, and be rich in good workes, and readie to distribute, and communicate</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>19</bibl> Laying vp in ſtore for themſelues a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the time to come, that they may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ne eternall life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Lord Ieſus Chriſt told his Apoſtles that it is eaſier for a Camel to goe through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of God, <hi>Math.</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. The Diſciples when they heard this were exceedingly amazed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Who then can be ſaued? For in deede they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue more credit to this ſpeech of Chriſt then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men commonly do, who are little amazed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at when they do heare it though it might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch them neerer then the Apoſtles who were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18261:9"/> poore. But he beheld them, and ſaid vnto them with men this is vnpoſſible, but with God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things are poſſible. Whereby it is euident, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> although riches do make it hard to be ſaued, yea vnpoſſible with men, not that the blame is to be imputed to the riches, but to mans corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for <hi>S. Marke</hi> reporteth that Chriſt ſaid, how hard is it for them that truſt in riches to enter into the kingdome of God? yet there is a paſſage and a way opened to heauen for the rich by the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power of God, with whome all things are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. From hence it is, that the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> doth inſtruct and warne <hi>Timothie,</hi> and in him all the Miniſters of the Goſpell, how they muſt deale with the rich men of this world. For if there were no poſſibilitie for them or any of them to be ſaued, it had bene vtterly in vaine to ſpeake of them as he doth: and if the paſſage to life were eaſie for them, what ſhould there neede a ſeuerall precept about them, and ſo vehement a charge to be giuen? Let rich men giue heed to this precept, if they tender their owne ſaluation, for heere is ſhewed a great wonder, namely, how the Camel ſhall get through the eye of a needle, that is, how they which abound in riches ſhall get to heauen, a matter of greater weight then all their poſſeſſions heere in the world.</p>
            <p>This text of ſcripture that we may come to handle it, is to be deuided into two parts, the former of them is in two verſes, containing the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18261:9"/> charge that muſt be giuen to rich men, namely, that they be not high minded, nor truſt in vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine riches, but in the liuing God, and doe good to others, that they may be rich in good workes, &amp;c. The latter part is in one verſe, ſhewing the great fruite and commoditie which they ſhall reape if they obey the charge that is giuen vnto them: for as he ſaith, they ſhall lay vp in ſtore for themſelues a good foundation againſt the time to come, and attaine eternall life. To come then a little neerer to the opening of the matter, the former part, which is the precept or charge doth deuide it ſelfe into two members, the one ſetting foorth what they muſt take heed of to eſchew, euen two moſt peſtiferous vices, loftines of mind, and vaine truſt in riches: the other oppoſing to thoſe two vices three excellent vertues which they muſt practiſe, that is, truſt in the liuing God, liberalitie or bountifulnes in diſtributing to thoſe which be in neede, and facilitie of maners. Thus may we looke vpon the ſumme of the whole matter, and now let vs proceede more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charge them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that are rich in this world, &amp;c.</hi> The parties to whome this charge is to be giuen are named the rich in this world, where <hi>S. Paule</hi> euen of purpoſe doth vſe this ſpeech in this world to pull them downe a little euen in the very entrance, and to abate their lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe. For there be two ſorts of rich men, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18261:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> one ſort are rich in this world, the other are rich (as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Luke 12. ver. 21.</hi>) to God. Now if we could ſee how farre they that be rich vnto God doe excell them that are but rich in this world, it would take them downe a little, and it would correct that peruerſe reſpecting of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and blinde iudgement which is in vs. For when he ſaith, in this world, oppoſing it to the world to come, he noteth the vanitie and the baſenes of earthlie riches, that there is no cauſe why any ſhould be puffed vp by them, if they were not more then blinded: and as <hi>S. Iames</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fault, Chapt. 2. men ſhould not haue their eyes ſo dazeled to eſteeme highlie of rich men, although they be vngodly, euen for the very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall pomp and glorie of their riches, and to deſpiſe the poore, although they be neuer ſo rich in faith, and in the precious gifts and graces of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie ſpirit. This for the perſons to whom the precept is directed. Now for the manner. Hee willeth (as ye ſee) <hi>Timothie</hi> to charge or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Is this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, Poore men in deede may be commaunded, but who ſhal commaund the rich, eſpecially the great Lords and Ladies? Shall the miniſters of the Goſpell take ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vpon them as to commaund ſuch? Yea verely. For albeit they be much inferior to them in the world, yet he that hath ſent them, whoſe Ambaſſadors they are, is moſt high aboue all, and in his name and authoritie they are to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund
<pb facs="tcp:18261:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> them: and the greateſt that ſhall deſpiſe and diſobey the charge, ſhall ſmart for it, ſeeing they deſpiſe not man, but God from whome it commeth. <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the king of Iuda (ſaith the holie Ghoſt) humbled not himſelfe before <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> the Prophet, at the commandement of the Lord, <hi>2. Chron. 36.12.</hi> therefore he was taken by the Chaldeans, his ſonnes were ſlaine before his face, his eyes then put out, and he caried in chaines to <hi>Babel, 2. King. 25.7.</hi> Furthermore, when <hi>S. Paule</hi> willeth the miniſters to lay this charge vpon the rich men, it argueth two things, euen the waightines of the matter, and the great difficultie to be performed, for were it not euen vpon the waight of their eternall ſaluation, ſo that in deede rich men can not be ſaued vnleſſe they obay this precept, <hi>S. Paule</hi> would not be ſo vrgent. And were it not that rich men are ſlow and wonderfull hard to be brought to this thing, yea euen as the Camell to be drawen through the eye of a needle, why ſhould the holie Apoſtle will vs to charge, to commaund, or to denounce vnto them that they do thus and thus? Why did he not ſay, moue them, put them in minde, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort or intreate them, (all which are to be done in deede) but he ſaith, commaund them. Heere we may ſee that the Preachers of the Goſpell ought to be farre from flattering the rich and great men of the world. They muſt charge and commaund them in the name of the Lord that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18261:11"/> they be not high minded, nor truſt in vncertaine riches, &amp;c. Noblemen haue their Chaplaines which attend vpon them in their houſes, ſhall they commaund their Lords the things which <hi>S. Paule</hi> heere willeth? Surely if they be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Chriſt, if they haue a ſyncere care to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his glorie, they muſt needes do it, for their Lords haue neede to be charged in the name of the moſt high God; but if they ſeeke themſelues, and their worldly preferment, then will they flatter and be afraide for to diſpleaſe, not caring much whether their Lords go to heauen or to hell, ſo they may ſerue their owne turne, and get liuings and dignities.</p>
            <p>And now come to the two vices which they muſt be charged to eſchew that haue the goods of this preſent world, namely loftines of minde, and truſt in riches, what ſhall we ſay of theſe, are they ſo heinous? Surely they be two vices ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, ſo peſtilent, and ſo deteſtable in the ſight of Almightie God, as none almoſt can be more. They be vices which are moſt iniurious not only to men, but alſo to the high maieſtie of God, and which he doth in deede highly accurſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne. How then is it poſſible that they ſhould be ſaued, in whome theſe vices do raigne? It may be ſaid, are not men of poore or meane eſtate ſubiect to theſe vices? Yes verely, but the rich are more ſubiect, they be in greater danger, and more hardlie drawen from them. True it is that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18261:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> pride, ambition, vaine-glorie, and loftines of minde, was that which the Serpent did ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Eue</hi> withall, bearing her in hand, that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the forbidden fruite <hi>Adam</hi> and ſhe ſhould be like God, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3. We all euen by inheritance haue receiued the poiſon thereof conueied vnto vs, it ſticketh moſt deepely in our nature, and is euen with the laſt ſinnes which are caſt out. Which may appeare by that which <hi>S. Paule</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of himſelfe, who being taken vp into the third heauen, euen as he ſaith, into Paradiſe, yet leaſt he ſhould be lifted vp or ſwell through the abundance of reuelations, there was giuen vnto him the prick in the fleſh, the angell of Satan to buffet him, <hi>2. Cor. 12.</hi> All then are by nature high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, but the rich men are more ſubiect vnto it, and more hardlie brought from it, becauſe the corrupt nature of man taketh occaſion by riches to be lifted vp further in pride, and to ſwell with loftines of minde. Riches and worldlie dignities are not of the eſſence of man, they be but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts or things accidentarie, and yet they that poſſeſſe them are ſo lifted vp in their minde (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they be renued by grace) that they do euen as if they were of another blood, contemne and deſpiſe others that haue them not. The words of men do manifeſtlie bewray this their pride and contempt: for if men be poore and in meane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, though rich in faith, and the image of God ſhining in them, they terme them the baſe raſcall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18261:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſort. But what do I mention the iniurie which the loftie minde doth offer vnto men, ſeeing it is lifted vp farre higher euen againſt God himſelfe? For marke what the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Pſal. 73.</hi> when he hath noted the proſperitie of wicked men, he addeth that pride is euen as a chaine vnto them: and they ſet their mouth againſt heauen, they ſtick not to blaſpheme God, and their tongue walketh through the earth. The loftie minde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo arrogateth to it ſelfe that which is due to God alone, for it doth not render glorie to him, but glorieth in it ſelfe. Wherefore it is no meruaile that the ſcripture ſpeaketh of pride and loftines of minde as of a thing moſt deteſtable in Gods ſight. <hi>Euery one that is of a loftie minde</hi> (ſaith Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) <hi>is an abomination to the Lord, Prouerb. 16. ver. 5. God reſiſteth the proude</hi> (ſaith the holie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>and giueth grace to the lowlie, 1. Pet. 5. ver. 5.</hi> Then let thoſe which are rich in this world (if they haue any care at all in them to be ſaued) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this charge heere giuen by <hi>S. Paul,</hi> that they be not high minded. Let them imitate holie king <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>Lord I am not high minded, I haue no prowde looke, &amp;c. I am as a wained childe, Pſal. 131.</hi> And let them alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what our Sauiour ſaith in the Goſpell, <hi>Except ye conuert and become as children, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to the other vice, that they truſt not in vncertaine riches. A vice moſt foule and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18261:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> which all men are prone vnto like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but the rich men moſt in danger, and not ſo eaſily drawne from it as poore men may. This vice is ſomewhat more cloſe then loftines of minde, I meane the vglines of it is not ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant vnto men: yet it is not inferior thereunto, yea, it is euen the roote from whence that other doth ſpring and grow vp. For what lifteth vp the minde of the rich, but this, that they haue ſuch wings to mount vp aloft withall aboue others, ſuch feathers to truſt vnto? Their riches are their ſtrong hold of defence, by which they imagine themſelues happie and in ſafetie. But how fooliſh they are, and how vaine this their confidence is, the holie Apoſtle noteth by calling them vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine riches. They forſake that which is certaine and infallible, euen the liuing God, in whome, whoſoeuer truſteth ſhall neuer be confounded, and truſt in that which is vncertaine and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. That they which truſt in riches forſake the liuing God, it is euident: for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>No man can ſerue two maiſters, but he muſt cleaue to the one and forſake the other, or &amp;c. you can not ſerue God and riches, Math. 6.</hi> And touching the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of riches (for that is the Apoſtles phraſe) it doth ariſe partlie from the nature of the riches themſelues, and partly from the ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe that do poſſeſſe them. The vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie that ariſeth from the riches themſelues is noted by Chriſt <hi>Math. 6. ver. 19.</hi> where he vſeth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18261:13"/> it as a reaſon to diſſwade men from the inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate loue of riches, ſaying, <hi>lay not vp for your ſelues, treaſures in earth, where moth and ruſt do corrupt, and where theeues breake through and ſteale.</hi> And <hi>Salomon</hi> doth as it were compare riches to a bird, that getteth out of the cage and flieth vp paſt mens reach, ſaying, <hi>trauaile not too much to be rich, but ceaſe from thy wiſedome. Wilt thou caſt thine eyes vpon it which is nothing? for riches taketh her to her wings as an Eagle, and flieth vp into the heauen, Prouerb. 23. ver. 4.5. Riches are ſubiect vnto many caſualties: who can aſſure himſelfe that he ſhall hold that the next yeare which he doth this, though he liue?</hi> How vaine then is that truſt which men do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in ſo vncertaine things? but yet there is a greater vncertaintie which ariſeth from the men that poſſeſſe them: for when one is ſo rich that there is no likelihoode that he may be ſuddainlie ſtript of that he hath, but if the theeues do breake through and ſteale plentie, and much doth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and come to naught of it ſelfe, yet it is not felt, but he can ſtill ſay, ſoule, thou haſt much goods laid vp for many yeares, eate, drinke, and take thy paſtime, <hi>Luke 12. ver. 19.</hi> yet he is not certaine: for looke what followeth there in Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> but God ſaide vnto him, <hi>O foole, this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt prouided?</hi> The rich men that are high minded, and glorie in their riches do take themſelues to be the only wiſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18261:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> men vnder heauen, but God ſaith to euery one of them, <hi>Thou foole.</hi> And verely their follie is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great in forſaking the Lord God, who is almightie and liueth for euer, and truſting to corruptible things, which are altogether deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Well it may be many rich men will little be moued with this reaſon of the vncertaintie of riches, for they will make them as certaine as they can to their poſteritie, and hope to inioy them long. They may be deceiued in both, but let it be they liue long, and their poſteritie after them, yet let them conſider how horrible a thing it is to giue that to riches, which they ſhould giue only to the liuing God. For ought not all men to truſt in God and in none other? Then when they put their truſt in riches, and make them euen as the ſtay of their life, and as the onely ſtaffe which they haue to leane vpon, they do in deede make riches their god. This may ſeeme an hard ſpeech, but I do not ſpeake it of mine owne head: for what ſaith the holie ſcripture, let men conſider well, doth it not call couetouſnes idolatrie? <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ. 3. ver. 5.</hi> And why is it idolatrie, but that the couetous man ſetteth his heart vpon his riches, truſteth in them, ſtayeth vpon them, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an idol of them which he ſo worſhippeth in ſtead of God? What a thunderbolt is this, that the couetous worldly men do quite forſake the true God, and in his ſtead do worſhip an idol? If mens harts were not harder then flint, or then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18261:14"/> the Adamant, it would make them tremble and quake. But men cannot be perſwaded, that they do put their truſt in riches: they know right well (they ſay) that they be vncertaine, they know that they themſelues muſt dye: yea, they can go further and in ſome ſort acknowledge with the holie Prophet, that man walketh in a vaine ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that he diſquieteth himſelfe in vaine, and that he heapeth vp riches and can not tell who ſhall gather them. Well notwithſtanding all this let it come to the iuſt triall. Do not they truſt in riches whoſe heart is more bent to ſeeke after them, then it is to ſeeke after God, or after hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie things? Doth not a man make that his god which he loueth beſt, or in which he doth moſt delight? Or which is a mans chiefe god, is not that which he doth truſt moſt vnto, and which he moſt cleaueth vnto? Then conſider this, if a worldlie man hold riches; he is ſafe, he is merie and glad in his heart, he hath to ſtay vpon, though his conſcience do tell him that God is diſpleaſed with him, yea the ſinnes which he committeth, ſo he may come by riches, as often as he thinketh of death, and of iudgement, do make that God is euen a terror vnto him, ſo farre off he is from delighting in God. Yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, rather then he will faile of riches, he doth proceede to lay hold of them by what way ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and ſo maketh the Lord God his vtter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, euen for his oppreſſion, for his extortion, for
<pb facs="tcp:18261:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> his briberie, for his vſurie, for his falſehood, and for his vnmercifull dealing toward the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. Tell him of this, doth it any thing at all ſtop his courſe? Iudge then indifferentlie, when a man doth forſake one to obtaine an other, doth he not meane to forſake the leſſer to chooſe the greater? Then when men do by all thoſe vices forſake God to lay hold of riches, do they not manifeſtlie declare that they eſteeme the more preſent diuinitie to be in riches? Is not there the God in deede which they can truſt vnto, and ſafely (as they thinke) reſt in, if they may lay hold on him? If they may retaine worldlie wealth, nothing can make them quaile, but they ſeeme to themſelues right happie, howſoeuer the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtand betweene God and their conſcience: but if they feare the loſſe of all or of the greateſt part of earthlie goods, they be ſtraightway in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſorrow and cry out that they be vtterlie vndone. O how can men be ſaued while they ſtand in this eſtate, being either high minded, or truſting in vncertaine riches! Is not the way to heauen vnto them as the eye of a ſmall needle is vnto an huge Camell? This is the very high way to hell, euen the broad way in which they walke: let them therefore harken what vertues the holie Apoſtle calleth them vnto, when they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and forſaken thoſe two moſt peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vices, which make the way to heauen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable to them: the firſt is, that they truſt in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18261:15"/> liuing God. <hi>S. Paule</hi> doth then call them away from a dead idol vnto a liuing God. For what are riches when men repoſe their truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in them, but a dead idol? The Lord God of heauen, he is the true and liuing God, it is he that giueth vs all things abundantly to inioy, and he that will haue life, or the ſtay of his life, muſt reſt only vpon him. The liuing God is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life, he hath giuen vnto vs our life, which as Chriſt ſaith is more worth then meat, <hi>Math.</hi> 6. <hi>ver. 25.</hi> and if he hath giuen vnto vs the greater, will he denie vnto vs the leſſer, if we truſt in him? Now as he is the fountaine and author of life, and giueth all things that belong thereunto, ſo if men could ſtedfaſtly truſt in him, they ſhould not be deſtitute; for he is able, ſeeing (as it is written <hi>Pſal. 24.) The earth is the Lords &amp; all that is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi> And he hath tyed himſelfe by promiſe vnto all that do put their truſt in him. <hi>Let your conuerſation</hi> (ſaith the holy Ghoſt) <hi>be without couetouſnes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing content with ſuch things as ye haue: for he hath ſaid, <hi>I will not leaue thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> So that we may boldly ſay, <hi>the Lord is my helper, I will not feare what man may do vnto me. Hebr. 13.5.6.</hi> He doth feede the fowles of the ayre, and cloath the graſſe of the field, then how much more will he feede and cloath men which truſt in him, being created after his owne image, and for whoſe vſe alſo he made the world? But how farre off are men from hauing this ſure truſt in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18261:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> the liuing God? alas it is lamentable to ſpeake. They can ſee and they can feele riches, but he is inuiſible, they can not ſee him: yea, but he hath giuen his word and his promiſe which is infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible. It is vnpoſſible that God ſhould lye or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, if they had the eyes of their minde but halfe as cleere as they haue their carnall eyes they might ſee this. Some man will obiect, that ſundrie which haue truſted in the Lord haue bin very poore. That is true, the holie Scripture doth afford ſundrie examples, the Lord ſeeth it is beſt for them, and men ought to reſt in his will, ſeeing he maketh pouertie a meane to bring them to glorie. It will be ſaid further, ſuch a truſt in God, or the pretenſe of ſuch a truſt may make men negligent and idle. That is not ſo, for true faith in God doth bring forth true obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: and God doth forbid idlenes and negligence, commanding men to vſe all mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate care and diligence in their callings, but that truſting in the liuing God, draweth theſe vertues which follow in the text with it, euen liberalitie and bountifulnes to the poore, with facilitie of maners, for that which is tranſlated to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, may be expounded of facilitie of maners: for when men are puffed vp, and be high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, becauſe of the abundance of their riches in which they repoſe a vaine confidence, their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are rough and ſterne, they cannot liue in common ſocietie, they cannot (as <hi>S. Paule</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18261:16"/> place willeth) make themſelues equall to them of the lower ſort, but touching this vertue I meane to ſpeake no more. And while men truſt in, their riches, making them the ſtaffe and ſtay of their life, and of their poſteritie, how is it poſſible that they ſhould be liberall, and rich in good works, and readie to diſtribute? will a man willinglie part with that which he doth repoſe his truſt in and maketh it his god? no, pluck riches from a worldlie minded man, and it is vnto him euen as if you ſhould teare out his bowels: for if he haue neuer ſo much, yet he feareth he ſhall not haue inough to hold out. If he diſtribute any thing to the poore, it is by compulſion of the lawes; or elſe that he is loath to be deemed too too miſerable. Doth not reaſon teach, that the more is taken from the heape, the leſſe remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth? A great veſſell with often drawing, is emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied and made dry. Theſe be the thoughts of worldlie minded men which truſt in riches: but if they once forſake that their vaine confidence, and fixe their hope in the liuing God, hauing their eyes opened to behold how it is he that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all things abundantly to inioy, then will they beleeue his word and promiſe, that plenteous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie ordered with godlie diſcretion ſhall not deminiſh but increaſe their very worldly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. What, ſhall plentifull giuing increaſe riches to the giuer? This may ſeeme a Paradox. For what reaſon is it that diſperſing and ſcatring
<pb facs="tcp:18261:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> abroad ſhould increaſe a mans wealth? He that doth ſhew mercie to the poore may (as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> heere teacheth) be rich in good workes: but can he be the richer alſo in the world? Can a man both keepe his goods, and giue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way? Yea that he may. For do you not ſee how the husbandman doth in ſeede time diſperſe and ſcatter his ſeed, yea, euen burie it in the ground, ſo that to mans reaſon (but that we ſee it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth otherwiſe to paſſe) it would ſeeme to be caſt away and vtterly loſt: and by the bleſſing of God he receiueth it againe ten fold, yea often times a great deale more. Yea but is the liberall diſtributing to the poore, like the ſowing of wheate or barley, ſhall it alſo yeeld an increaſe? if rich men were ſo perſwaded, they would fall to ſowing apace. Surely they might be ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, for the word of truth that can not lye doth tell them ſo. <hi>Salomon in Eccleſiaſt. chap. 11.</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many dayes thou ſhalt finde it. Giue a portion to ſeuen, and alſo to eight, ſeeing thou knoweſt not what euil ſhall come vpon the earth.</hi> The ſcripture ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times doth call ſeede bread, becauſe bread is made of it. And <hi>Salomon</hi> willeth to caſt this ſeed vpon the waters, that is, vpon groundes which are well watred and fertile. Admoniſhing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all rich men to be wiſe in imitating the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen: for as they make choiſe of good grounds to ſow their corne, to the end that in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18261:17"/> time they may receiue the greater increaſe, ſo would he haue theſe to ſow to diſperſe and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their riches by almes deeds vpon the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, the widow, and the fatherleſſe, eſpeciallie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> godlie poore, that be (as <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith) of the houſhold of faith, for theſe be the well wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and fruiteful ground, and after many dayes they ſhall finde it. Such as do ſow vpon this ground, do ſow vnto the Lord: and by his ſingular bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing they ſhall receiue great increaſe. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in <hi>Pſal. 112.</hi> ſetting forth the bleſſednes of the godlie man, ſaith thus, <hi>He hath diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and giuen to the poore, and his righteouſnes remaineth for euer.</hi> Now marke how <hi>S. Paule</hi> doth applie this ſaying of the Prophet, <hi>2. Cor. 5.</hi> for perſwading them to be plenteous in libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, he vſeth this compariſon, <hi>He that ſoweth ſparinglie ſhall reape ſparinglie, and he that ſoweth bountifullie, ſhall reape bountifullie.</hi> All men do know that the Farmer which doth ſow but a little ſeede, muſt needes haue but a little harueſt Euen ſo he ſheweth, that ſuch as do ſow but a little in almes-deedes and workes of charitie to the poore, ſhall alſo haue a ſmall harueſt. And then further to ſhew that the ſame harueſt or reaping which he ſpeaketh of, is not only in the world to come, or in the riches of good works, but alſo in the bleſſing of God vpon their worldlie goods; and to take away the doubt which men haue, that if they giue liberally, they
<pb facs="tcp:18261:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come to pouertie themſelues, he addeth: <hi>And God is able to make you plentifull in all grace, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alwayes hauing all ſufficiencie in all things, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nd in euery good worke:</hi> as it is written, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th diſperſed abroad and giuen to the poore; his righteouſnes remaineth for euer.</hi> We ſee then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>w <hi>S. Paule</hi> expoundeth this clauſe <hi>(his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſnes)</hi> to be his beneuolence, or bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifulnes in giuing a lines, ſhall remaine for euer. As if he ſhould ſay, the more lie doth ſcatter and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe abroade, the more God doth make his riches to abound, and giueth him all ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie then to ſinfull that which is written, that his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bilitie to be liberall ſhall neuer faile. And to conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de this yet further, the holie Apoſtle v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſimilitude of the husbandman, who by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing his ſeed doth receiue increaſe: for thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e addeth in verſe 10. <hi>Alſo he that findeth foode in the ſower, will minister likewiſe bread for foode, and multiplie your ſeede, and increaſe the fruites of your beneuolence: that on all parts ye may be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b vnto all liberalitie, which cauſeth through vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nksgiuing vnto God.</hi> What can be more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble then this promiſe of Gods bleſſing (if rich men could caſt off vnbeliefe, and giue credit v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to it) to moue vnto liberality, that they ſhall not only thereby become rich in good works, but alſo that God will ſo bleſſe and encreaſe their worldly ſubſtance, that they ſhall alwaies
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18261:18"/> haue abundance, both for their owne vſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d alſo to giue vnto the poore? What hardn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of heart is in men, that can not beleeue God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this thing, but ſay ſtill, If I giue very faſt, I may come to pouerty my ſelfe? Whatſoeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then God promiſeth, this is ſtill the concluſion, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> men will truſt more to their riches then to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> promiſe: their riches they will holde as fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as they can: there is the ſure God, as they thinke. Is there no helpe? is there no re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> for this ſo deadly and ſo dangerous diſeaſe Surely if it be poſſible to be remedied (as hee haue ſhewed before, it ſhall be in ſome) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy is ſet downe by the holy Apoſtle in the laſt verſe of this Text, where he ſaith, <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for themſelues a good foundation againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come, that they may attaine eternall life.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (a we noted) the ſecond part of the Texte, which declareth the incomparable benefite and fruit, which the riche men ſhall reape, if they ſhall ſhew themſelues obedient to this charge it is a benefite to haue that bleſſing of God in this life which is promiſed vnto the liberall: but this is farre greater, beeing the bleſſing of all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which the Apoſtle here noteth: then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we here obſerue, that riches, if men coulde vſe them, are inſtruments of great happines: for thereby they haue habilitie to be rich in good works, which is to be rich vnto God, euen the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18261:18"/> chiefe riches of all. The holy Scripture ſetteth this forth vnder diuers phraſes of ſpeech, as firſt S. Paul here ſaith, <hi>They ſhall lay vp for themſelues a good foundation againſt the time to come.</hi> A good foundation is the ground-worke of a ſure and permanent building. No man by the multitude of his worldly goods can make ſo ſure worke here, but it will decay and come to vtter ruine, how ſoeuer men are builded, and doe imagine that they can builde their neſt ſo high and ſo ſure, as that it ſhal continue. But for the time to come or againſt that time, the rich in this world may, if they haue grace and true wiſedome to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their riches, make the foundation of a moſt happy building, which ſhal neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay,) Chriſt Ieſus vſeth an other compariſon to ſet forth this ſame matter, <hi>Luke 12. ver. 33.</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Sell your goods and giue almes: make you bags that ſhall neuer waxe old, a treaſure in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſhall neuer faile, whither the thiefe cannot approch, and where the moth doth not corrupt.</hi> And <hi>Luke. 10. ver. 9.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Make you friends of the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Mammon, that when ye ſhall haue neede, they may receiue you into euerlaſting habitations.</hi> This is indeed all one with that which <hi>S. Paule</hi> here ſaith, <hi>Laying vp in ſtore for themſelues a good fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation againſt the time to come.</hi> Indeede that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt is notable to be obſerued: marke therefore how he bringeth it in. He vſeth a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18261:19"/> ſaying: There was a rich man that had a Stewarde, who was accuſed vnto him that he had waſted his goods, and hee willed him to giue his accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, for he could no longer be ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. The ſteward being now in a ſtraight, and knew not how to liue when he ſhould forgo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his office, at length vſeth this craftie dealing the goeth to all thoſe which did owe anye great ſummes to his Maſter, and did ſtrike off and forgiue them a great part, that ſo befriending them, they might, when hee was out of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ſhewe friendſhip to him, and receyue him into their houſes. Our Sauiour hereupon ſaith, that the children of this world are wiſer in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r generation then the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of light: And then he willeth vs to imitate this vniuſt ſteward (not in that vniuſt courſe which he tooke) but ſeing we are all but ſtewardes, and muſt out of our ſtewardſhip, he willeth vs to bee ſo wiſe as to make vs friends of the vnrighteous Mammon, that when we ſhall need or fayle, that is, when we ſhall goe out of our ſtewardſhip, they may receiue vs into euerlaſting habitations. But what meaneth that, howe ſhall wee make vs friendes of the vnrighteous Mammon which ſhall receiue vs into euerlaſting habitations? Or who bee thoſe friends? It is a parabolicall ſpeech. Yee ſee how the ſteward with his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters goods by an vniuſt way made him frends:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18261:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo our Lord doth aduiſe vs, which are but ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vnder God ouer the riches which wee doe poſſeſſe, to make vs friends after a lawfull and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable way with our Lords goods, that is, by diſtributing and giuing almes to thoſe that be in neceſſitie. This is a thing pleaſing to God, vnder whome we doe hold our ſteward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and the friendes which we then make, are the good workes themſelues, which ſhall follow and accompanie vs at our death, when we goe out of our ſtewardſhip, and be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with eternall glorie: for ſo God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, that they which bring forth good works, euen the teſtimonies and fruites of a true and liuely faith, ſhall bee rewarded with eternall glorie, which is it that hee ſaith, that they may receiue you into euerlaſting habitations: and as <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith here, <hi>Laying vp in ſtore a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may attaine eternall life.</hi> To make bagges then which ſhall neuer wax olde, to make friendes of the vnrighteous Mammon, which may receiue vs into euerlaſting habitations, and to lay vp in ſtore a good foundation againſt the time to come, that we may attaine eternall life, are all to one effect; a wonderfull happie thing to rich men if they can lay hold of it. But alas if we behold the preſent eſtate, ſhall we thinke that men doe belieue this? The wealth that many
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18261:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> doe flow it, is verie great, and multitudes are pined with extreame miſerie, and few there be which doe liberally diſtribute: yea contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we finde verie many, that care not ſo they may enrich themſelues, what become of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poore. This thing is euident by the ſelling of their corne &amp; other commodities, which they thinke they neuer haue enough for, although the price be vnreaſonable, What an extreame blindneſſe, and folly is this, yea what a wofull miſerie, that the men of this world which haue plentie of riches doe not onely depriue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of a double bleſſing? the one vpon their goods and poſteritie in this life, according as God hath promiſed, if they ſhall diſtribute to the poore, and be riche in good workes, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the reward of eternall glorie in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens; but alſo caſt themſelues into a double ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie, the one in depriuing themſelues of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glorie, the other in deſtroying their worldly eſtate: for if their riches doe ſtand and continue with them for their owne life, which ſundrie times falleth out otherwiſe, becauſe God doth accurſe riches ſo gotten, yet do their children ſcatter and conſume them at leaſt within a few generations, as dayly experience ſheweth in a number, and ſo you may ſee their double miſerie. Well may ſome man ſay, doth not this make for the Popiſh doctrine of merite
<pb facs="tcp:18261:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> and iuſtification by mens owne workes? when a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men deedes to the poore doe lay vp in ſtore a good foundation againſt the time to come, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t they may attaine eternall life: when bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull giuing doth make bagges full of treaſure which ſhall neuer wax olde: and when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, to the needie doth make friendes that ſhall receiue vs into euerlaſting habitations? are not men then iuſtified by theſe their works, or doe not their good deedes deſerue or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite eternall glorie? Theſe good workes are the teſtimonies of a true, liuely and iuſtifying faith being plenteouſly and rightly done, they ſhew that the doer is a liuely member of Chriſt Ieſus who is our righteouſneſſe, <hi>1. Cor. 1.</hi> being led by his ſpirite. And touching merites of workes, there bee no deedes ſo excellent as that they can deſerue ſo great glorie: ſo great reward is of the meere mercie, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the free grace of God, who hath promiſed ſuch reward vnto good workes. This foundation againſt the time to come, theſe bagges that neuer waxe olde, and the friendes that wee muſt make by almes deedes, are all ſuch workes of mercie as doe teſtifie a true and liuely faith, being the vnſeperable fruites thereof, which God will plentifully reward with glorie and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The doers of theſe being not forgetful hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, but doers of the worke, ſhall, as the holy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18261:21"/> Ghoſt ſaith, be bleſſed in their deede. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>It may be here demanded, ſeeing works do not iuſtifie before God, but are the fruites of thoſe which are iuſtified, Chriſt being our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, when we haue the full pardon of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſinnes in his bloud, and are clothed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bedience imputed vnto vs, whether men ſhall haue the greater glory, according to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and multitude of their good workes? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that according to the meaſure of Faith which a man hath, ſo are his works: &amp; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his faith and his works be, the greater ſhall be his rewarde in glorie. If this were not ſo, how ſhould <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſay, <hi>They which ſow ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall reape ſparingly, and they which ſow plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſhall reape plenteouſly. 2. Cor. 9.</hi> Yea howe ſhould he ſay in this place, that he woulde haue thoſe that bee rich in this worlde charged to do good, and to be rich in good works? If there be not a more plenteous reward to the greater and more plenteous good workes, how ſhould any, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others be ſaid to be rich in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is ſtrange &amp; wonderful, that rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not be brought to ſee this, and to vſe their riches to their beſt aduantage, but doe indeede let ſlip their happines. They can willingly beſtowe great coſt in building faire houſes: it doth not grieue them to beſtow very much alſo in gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous apparell: and they recken not what they
<pb facs="tcp:18261:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> lay out in delicate fare, both vpon themſelues and vpon others that bee wealthie: but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a little more then ordinarie vppon thoſe that be poore and in miſerie, is very gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe they doe account that to be loſt or caſt away: whereas in verie deede, there is nothing which can be laide out to anie great profite, but that which is ſpent vpon the poore: for houſes, apparel and meates doe periſh with their vſe, they be tranſitory and vaine: but the reward promiſed by the Lord is a treaſure that ſhal neuer come vnto an end. Thoſe former do appertaine but vnto the ſatisfying of carnall luſtes: but mercie ſhewed to the needy, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vp glorie in the Heauens. There is a verie great difference betweene theſe two: but men are led by ſenſe and not by ſounde wiſedome: and that cauſeth them to make ſo bad a choice. They feele the ſweetnes of riches for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time: they are ſure of thoſe goodly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which they enioy by them.</p>
            <p>But to be rich in good workes, and ſo to lay vp a good foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the time to come, that they may attaine eternall life; this is not perceiued by ſenſe, this they can not skil of, and therefore they doe little trouble themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. At the day of iudgement, this time to come, ſhall be preſent, and then this inuiſible foundation ſhall be ſeene: when Chriſt ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:18261:22"/> ſay to thoſe on his right hand: <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father, inherite the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world. For I was a hungred and ye gaue me meate, I thirſted and you gaue me drinke; I was a ſtranger and ye lodged<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> I was naked and ye clothed me: I was ſicke and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viſited me: I was in priſon, and ye came vnto me, Then ſhal the righteous anſwere, him ſaying: Lord, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaw we thee an hungred &amp; fed thee? or a thirſt &amp; gaue thee drinke? And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaw we thee a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and lodged thee? or naked and clothed thee? Or when ſawe we thee ſicke or in priſon, and came vnto thee? And the king ſhall anſwere and ſay vnto them. Verely I ſay vnto you, in as much as ye haue done it vnto one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren, ye haue done it to me. Math. 25. ver. 34.35.36.37.38.39.40, And goe ye curſed into euerlaſting fire, prepared for the deuil and his angels. For I was an hungred and ye gaue me no meate, I thirſted and ye gaue me no drinke, &amp;c. In as much as ye did i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me,</hi> a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing to ſee the blindnes in which men are. Who doth not accompt it the moſt happie thing that can befall a man, to giue to Chriſte when he is hungrie, or thirſtie, or naked, or ſicke, or in priſon? Againe, who is he that will not confeſſe it to be a moſt vile wretchednes, when a man doth ſet more by his riches, then by relieuing Chriſte?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now marke well, are not all that beleeue, the very members of Chriſtes myſticall bodie? Thou beholdeſt the poore that are ſicke or lame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou ſeeſt poore fatherleſſe childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that pine, and are readie to famiſh: theſe, for ought which thou knoweſt, may be the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Ieſus Chriſt. If then thou doeſt neglect and deſpiſe them, thou doeſt neglect and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe Chriſt. Is not this a moſt curſed thing that any man ſhould loue worldly traſh, euen for the filling of fleſhly luſtes, more then he loueth God or Chriſt? For if a man had any ſparke of lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in him vnto God, he muſt needes loue Chriſte in his members, he muſt needes loue his brother.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, Saint Iohn manifeſtly ſaith, <hi>He that hath this worldes good, and ſeeth his brother in neede, and ſhutteth vp his compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him? 1. Iohn. 3. ver. 17,</hi> O curſed loue of money, that caryeth men from the loue of God. It is no maruaile that Saint Paul ſaith, <hi>The loue of money is the root of all euils. 1. Tim. 6.10.</hi> For he ſaith there, that they which would be rich fall into temptation, and into a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and noyſome luſtes, which drowne men in deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and perdition. O will ſome man ſay, if the wordes of Saint Paul are ſo ſtrictly to be taken, how could ſome that haue bene prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb facs="tcp:18261:23"/> of the Goſpell, couet riches, and loue money ſo much as they haue done? Is it not found by common experience, that neuer any haue bene more couetous, or more loued mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or haue ſought riches and worldly pomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more then ſome that haue preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell? Shall we ſay, that ſuch Lighters walke in ſo dangerous a way? Doe ſuch forſake the true and liuing God, and worſhip an idol? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God is no reſpecter of perſons: ſuch are ſo farre off from all excuſe, that of all others they fall into the deepeſt condemnation: for while they take vpon them in wordes to ſet forth the glorious Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and giue ſo fowle example in deede, what doe they but pull downe the dignitie of the Goſpell, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the weake to ſtumble, and the blinde to wander out of the way?</p>
            <p>To returne to our matter for laying vp the good foundation againſt the time to come, I will conclude with two ſayings of the ſcripture, the one of king Salomon, the other of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Iſay. Thus ſaith Salomon, <hi>He that hath mercie vpon the poore, lendeth vnto the Lorde, and the Lorde will recompence him that which he hath giuen. Prouerbes, 19.17.</hi> And thus ſaith the Lord by Iſay: That thou deale thy bread to the hungrie, and that thou bring the poore that wander into thine houſe, when thou ſeeſt the
<pb facs="tcp:18261:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> naked, that thou couer him, and hide not thy ſelfe from thine owne fleſhe: then ſhall thy light breake forth as the morning, and thine health ſhall growe ſpeedily: Thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall goe before thee, and the glorie of the Lorde ſhall imbrace thee. Then ſhalt thou call, and the Lorde ſhall anſwere: thou ſhalt crie, and he ſhall ſay, heare am I. If thou take away from the middes of thee the yoake, the putting forth of the finger, &amp; wicked ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, if thou power out thy ſoule to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, and refreſh the troubled ſoule: then ſhall my light ſpring out of the darkenes, and thy darkenes ſhall be as the noone-day: And the Lorde ſhall guide thee continuallie, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy ſoule in drought, and make fatte thy bones: and thou ſhalt be like a watred garden, and like a ſpring of waters, whoſe waters faile not, and they ſhall be of thee that ſhall builde the waſt places, &amp;c. <hi>Iſay, chap. 58. verſe 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12.</hi> The Lorde for his ſonnes ſake giue vs grace to followe this holy precept, that we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne eternall life.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:24"/>
            <head>THE SECOND Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Iohn, Chap. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>7</bibl> For there are three which beare recorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> heauen, the Father, the word, and the holy ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>8</bibl> And there are three which beare record in the earth, the ſpirite, the water, and the bloud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and theſe three agree in one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>9</bibl> If we receyue the witnes of men, the witnes of God is greater: for this is the witnes of GOD which he teſtified of his ſonne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>10</bibl> Hee that beleeueth in that ſonne of God hath the witnes in himſelf: he that beleeueth not God hath made him a lyar, becauſe he beleeued n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the record that God witneſſed of that his ſonne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>11</bibl> And this is that recorde, that God hath giuen vnto vs eternall life, &amp; this life is in that his ſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>12</bibl> He that hath that ſonne, hath that life: and he that hath not that ſon of God hath not that life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>13</bibl> Theſe things haue I written vnto you that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in the name of the ſonne of God, that yee may know that ye haue eternall life, and that yee may beleeue in the name of that ſonne of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Verie worde of God is pure, Prou. 30.5. The whole Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure is giuen by diuine inſpiration, and is profitable &amp;c. 2. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16.</hi> And <hi>what ſoeuer things haue bene writen afore-time, haue bin wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning. Ro. 15.4.</hi> It is our dutie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> humble and obedient ſchollers of Chriſt, to giue care vnto euerie part of Gods word. And moreouer, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome parts thereof doe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally excell, ſo are wee the more willinglie to learn them. Such is this which I haue now read vnto you, as you may perceiue by the cauſe, for which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> affirmeth he wrote it, ſaying, <hi>Theſe things haue I write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you which beleeue in the name of that ſon of God, that ye may know that ye haue eternall life, and that ye may beleeue in the name of that ſonne of God. ver. 13.</hi> What higher point then this for a man to know that he ſhall be ſaued? What greater ioye and felicitie can be fall vnto any? Indeede many doe holde that it is vnpoſſible for anye man while hee liueth here, to knowe for certaintie that hee ſhall be ſaued. How can any man tell (ſay they) that he ſhall be ſaued? Can any goe vp to heauen, and there ſee that his name is written in the booke
<pb facs="tcp:18261:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> of life? The Papiſtes proceede yet further, and they ſay, it is pride &amp; wicked arrogancy for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man to affirme that he doth knowe he ſhall be ſaued. Humilitie (they ſay) doth teach men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to ſtand in doubt. Moſt true it is, that their doctrine of mens merites muſt needes breed all doubting: and pride intole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able it is for any man to ſay, he knoweth his owne good works doe merite or deſerue eternall glorie in the heauens, and that he is ſure he ſhall haue it for the ſame. But let theſe paſſe with their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian doctrine, &amp; giue eare to S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Theſe things haue I written, that ye may kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w that ye haue eternall life, and that ye may beleeue, &amp;c.</hi> But before we handle the words, let vs ſee how they depend vpon the former part of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>In the firſt verſe you ſee it is thus writen, <hi>Who ſoeuer beleeueth that Ieſus is the Chriſt, is borne of God.</hi> This is euen the ground of this whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, namely that the newe and ſpirituall birth goeth inſeparably with faith: for he ſaith, <hi>who ſo euer beleeueth that Ieſus is the Chriſt,</hi> ſpeaking of the true and liuely faith, he is borne of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo he is the child of God. Whereupon it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on the other ſide, that who ſoeuer is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, but committeth the deedes of the fleſh, though he ſeeme to beleeue, yet he hath not the true and liuely faith, but that which the
<pb facs="tcp:18261:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> holy Ghoſt calleth a dead faith, hee is not the childe of God. Then he addeth further, <hi>Euerie one that loueth him which begate, loueth him alſo which is begotten.</hi> This muſt needes be ſo, for it is as a principle in nature, whereby it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that whoſoeuer loueth not the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, he loueth not God: for he that entirely doeth loue the Father, cannot, but for his ſake, loue the children which are begotten of him. Then it is thus, hee that loueth not the children of God, is not borne of God, and therefore hee hath not the true faith in Chriſt. And he that is borne of God, hee loueth God, and therefore alſo he loueth his children, and by this he ſaith, we know we loue the children of God, when we loue God, and keepe his commandements. The triall that men loue Gods children is from hence, that they loue God: and the triall that we loue God is, if we keepe his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for ſo hee affirmeth in the third verſe, where he alſo ſaith, that the commandements of God are not grieuous, or heauie. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as Chriſt willeth vs to take his yoke vpon vs, adding further <hi>That his yoke is eaſie, and his burthen light. Math. 11.29.30.</hi> Is the law then eaſie to be kept? Surely there is nothing more grieuous to the vnregenerate man the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law of God for (as <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith) the law is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and wee are carnall, ſoulde vnder ſinne.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18261:26"/> 
               <hi>Rom. 7.14.</hi> There is ſuch a diſagreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the heauenly puritie of Gods law, and our corrupt and defiled nature, that when they meete, wee are ſo farre off from hauing anie power to fulfill the lawe, or any part of it, that by it the luſts of ſinne worke in our members, to bring forth fruite vnto death. <hi>Rom. 7.5.</hi> Not that the law is to be blamed, but as the Apoſtle there diſputeth at large, ſinne taketh occaſion by the law. It is not then <hi>S. Iohns</hi> meaning to teach, that the commandements be not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous or light and eaſie to the naturall man, for ſure to him they bee grieuous? How then? the commaundements are not grieuous to the ſpirituall man, to the regenerate man, euen to him that is borne of God, for ſo <hi>S. Iohn</hi> apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the matter, and rendereth a reaſon, in theſe words, <hi>Becauſe whatſoeuer is borne of God ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the world.</hi> By the world is meant what ſoeuer, either within vs or without vs is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and contrarie to Gods will: as chap. 2. ver. 16. of this Epiſtle, hee doth expound the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, to be in the world, and of the world. Then looke how far a man is regenerate, and borne of God, ſo farre hee ouercommeth and ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all vncleane luſtes, he hateth the remnants of them, and delighteth in the law of GOD. <hi>Rom. 7.15.22.</hi> How then can the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:18261:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> be grieuous vnto him? The luſtes of ſinne are ſweete to the natural man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the lawe which condemneth them is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous vnto him. But can they that are borne of God then perfectly fulfill the lawe, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come righteous in themſelues? In no wiſe. For then ſhould ſuch as are borne of God be without ſinne: but in the firſt chapter of this Epiſtle. ver. 8. he ſaith, <hi>If we ſay we haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs.</hi> In many thinges we ſinne all. <hi>Iam. 3. ver. 2. There is no man</hi> (ſaith Salomon) <hi>which ſinneth not. 1, King. 8.46. Yea no man can tell how often. Pſal. 19.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Saint Peter</hi> ſaide thus vnto ſuch as would haue men iuſtified by the lawe, <hi>Now therefore, why doe you tempt God, to laye a yoake vpon the necke of the diſciples, which neither our fathers, nor we are able to beare? Acts 15.10.</hi> Well, to proceede; <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> commeth neerer, and ſaith: <hi>This is the victorie that ouercommeth the world, euen our faith.</hi> There is then a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous excellencie in faith: for by it we ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the world, euen all the vncleane luſtes of ſinne: and by it we ouercome Sathan the prince of the world, who hath no power not authoritie but by thoſe luſtes. But now wee muſt vnderſtand, that this faith is onely the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of our victorie, for the whole matter and power of our victorie is in Chriſt, whome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18261:27"/> the faith layeth holde on: Wherefore he ſaith: Who is it that ouercommeth the world, but he which beleeueth that Ieſus is the ſonne of God? And then he ſheweth that there is the fulneſſe of victorie in Chriſt, becauſe he came both by water, and bloud. In the time of the lawe, there was figured by bloud, and by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the full ſatisfaction, and the full purification or cleanſing from all ſinne: both theſe are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Chriſt: he hath by his blood made full ſatisfaction of, and hee doth ſanctifie and purge his choſen from all vncleanneſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in him is a full victorie. For the curſe of the lawe being ſatisfied, and then we waſhed and ſanctified from all ſpotte, what power can Satan or death haue ouer vs? This being a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo great and waightie, and faith bearing vp the whole waight of it, moſt neceſſarie it is, that the faith it ſelfe haue a mightie &amp; ſure ground worke, or foundation to reſt vpon. That which beareth vp ſo mightie a building, muſt not reſt vpon a foundation that is from any creature: And therefore <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſheweth, that faith which is our victorie, is grounded vpon the teſtimonie of ſixe great witneſſes: of which, three are in heauen, and the other three in earth. The three which beare record in heauen, are the father, and the worde (that is the ſonne) and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt. Theſe three are one; that is, they doe
<pb facs="tcp:18261:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> all teſtifie one thing, or agree all in one. For what the father from heauen witneſſed of his ſonne, the ſame did the ſonne witnes of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the holy ghoſt alſo did confirme it.</p>
            <p>This is a moſt cleare place of ſcripture, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe heretikes which denied the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of perſons in the godhead, for if the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were not a diſtinct perſon from the Sonne and ſo the Sonne from the holy Ghoſt, howe could he ſay there bee three which beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in heauen? Then faith hath the witneſſe of God the father, of GOD the ſonne, and of God the holy Ghoſt to reſt vpon. Here is that ſure foundation which can not faile. They bee ſeducers which teach their ſchollers to ground their faith vppon men, as the Papiſtes which draw men from grounding their faith vpon the teſtimonie of God the father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, expreſſed and deliuered vnto vs in the ſcriptures, and will haue them reſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the authoritie of the Pope and his popiſh clergie. This teſtimonie of their owne, they proclaime to be ſound, and infallible, boaſting that they can not erre: the voice &amp; teſtimonie of God in the holy ſcriptures they charge to be darke, doubtful, and vncertaine: moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous wretches. Then he addeth that there be alſo three which beare record in earth, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and the water, and the bloud, and theſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18261:28"/> three agree in one. Where firſt it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, what ſpirit this is which is ioined with the water &amp; the bloud as a witnes vpon earth? Is it not the holy Ghoſt, one of the three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes from heauen? This is out of all doubt &amp; controuerſie that he ſpeaketh againe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. The ſpirite then is a double witnes, he is one of the three from heauen, and hee is one of the three vpon earth.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall demaund, how can this bee? Let them know that the holy ghoſt doth two waies beare witnes of Chriſt: firſt, together with the father and the ſonne from heauen in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt authority of the Diuine Maieſtie hee did beare recorde of Chriſt, and confirmed his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which he had taught with ſignes and wonders and manifold gifts. And then by his worke and grace in the hearts of men, when he lighteneth them, and applyeth vnto them the efficacie of the death and reſurrection of Chriſt. Let it not ſeeme ſtrange then that the holy Ghoſt is brought in as a double witnes, firſt as one of the three from heauen, and then as one of the three in earth, that is in the hearts of men: for if there were no more but the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thoſe three from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Chriſt ſhould not profite vs at al, becauſe we are not capable of our ſelues: and therefore the holy Ghoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as a witnes in earth applyeth vnto our hearts
<pb facs="tcp:18261:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> the power of the water &amp; the bloud by which Chriſt came: that is, the ſanctifying and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying power of his death: for he ſprinckleth the harts of the beleeuers with the bloud of Chriſt. The water, the bloud and the ſpirite then wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes one thing in the heart, euen that the whole ſatisfaction for ſinne, and al true holines is from Chriſt crucified. Hereby we may perceiue that the efficacie and power of Chriſts bloud in vs, is a witnes vnto vs of a true and liuely faith, and ſo of eternall life: becauſe the Spirite and the water and the bloude beare witneſſe in earth. Then he proceedeth to ſet forth the ſtablenes of the credite of theſe witneſſes, which he doth by a compariſon, ſaying: If we receiue the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of men, the witnes of God is greater. This is grounded vpon a cleare principle, which none can deny: for God in ſtedfaſt truth far exceeds men. We giue credite to a matter when two or three men which are reputed honeſt, doe vpon their ſolemne oath affirme that they did heare or ſee it done: if other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make doubt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as they haue ſworne, they hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues much iniured: for ſhal we not receiue or giue credite to the teſtimony of honeſt men vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their oths? How much more iniurie doe we to the God of all truth, whoſe witnes is greater then the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of all men, when we do not giue credite to the witnes which hee witneſſeth of his Sonne?
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18261:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> For the teſtimony of God is that which he hath witneſſed of his ſon. I neede not ſtand to open this, for it is meere brutiſhnes not to yeelde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. And here I pray you beholde againe the great and horrible wickednes and filthy blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of the Pope and his ſhauelings: which would make the teſtimony of men, yea euen the teſtimony of themſelues, (being wicked men) greater then the teſtimony of God. For what is the teſtimony of God by which he doth beare record of his ſonne, but his written word deliuered vnto vs by the Apoſtles &amp; Prophets? And where can wee haue the teſtimony which God witneſſeth of his ſon, but in thoſe ſacred Bookes? <hi>Search the Scriptures</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>for they beare record of mee. Iohn, 5.</hi> Now when the Papiſts do affirme (that the Scriptures haue no authority nor credite) vnto vs, but as their Pope and they do giue it, or commende them to bee beleeued: what doe they but ſet the witnes of men aboue the witnes of God? I will not ſtand here to rehearſe at large, but euen a little touch ſome of the vile and execrable ſpeeches of thoſe foule mouthed Papiſts, which to hold vp the Popiſh religion deface the cleare teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of God in the Scriptures, which are flat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: for beeing preſſed with the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt voice and teſtimony of God in his worde, they cry out, there is no certainty in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:18261:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> they be like a noſe of waxe, which you may turne which way you will, they be a dead letter, and a dumbe Iudge: and but that the Church commendeth them no more credite were to be giuen to the Scripture then to <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopes</hi> Fables. O moſt vile wretches, ſhall the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of God, which is greater then the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of men, haue no force, but as it receiueth from them? And then he addeth, <hi>Hee that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in that ſon of God hath the witnes in himſelfe.</hi> As he ſpake of the greatnes of the teſtimony of the Father, the word and the holy ghoſt, which is from heauen, in the former verſe: ſo now he ſheweth that who ſoeuer beleeueth that teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony from heauen, hath the teſtimony of the three witneſſes which beare recorde in earth within him. What is that? this it is: he that doth beleeue the witnes that GOD beareth of his ſonne, the witnes that Chriſt beareth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and which the holy Ghoſt hath alſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, which is all indeede but one teſtimony, the ſame hath the witnes alſo of the Spirite, of the water, and of the bloud within him. Marke then how theſe ſixe witneſſes doe meete toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to aſſure vs of one and the ſelfe ſame thing, euen this, that God hath giuen vnto vs eternall life, and that the ſame life is in his Sonne. For when the ſpirite of adoption, as <hi>S. Paule</hi> calleth him, <hi>Rom. 8.</hi> beareth witnes with the ſpirite of a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18261:30"/> man, that he is the ſonne of God, he doth it by making him feele the efficacie of the water &amp; bloud by which Chriſt came, that is the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his death and reſurrection in ſatisfaction for his ſinnes, and in ſanctification. Euerie one then which beleeueth aright hath the ſpirite of God in him, &amp; the liuely power of Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, which do witnes vnto him, that through Chriſt he is made the childe of God, and ſhall be ſaued. From hence we may learne what the nature of the true, liuelie and iuſtifying faith is, and whereby it is diſtinguiſhed or diſcerned from the hiſtoricall and dead faith: for if a man doe aſſent and beleeue, that all thoſe things are true which the father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt haue teſtified of Chriſt in the ſcriptures, and yet bee voide of the ſpirite and power of Chriſt vnto ſanctification (as many that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen learned men are) it is a manifeſt declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that his faith is but a dead faith, and not that which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh of here, when hee ſaith, <hi>He that belieueth hath the witneſſe in him ſelfe.</hi> And it followeth, hee that belieueth not God hath made him a lyer, becauſe he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not the record that God witneſſeth of his Sonne, as I noted before. Men which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted honeſt, (if they teſtifie vpon their oath, in a matter and be not belieued) wil hold them ſelues hardly dealt withall, and much iniured:
<pb facs="tcp:18261:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> how great is the iniurie then offered to God, when he hath borne record of his ſonne, and we doe not giue credite to his teſtimonie? He hath not onely promiſed vnto vs remiſſion of ſinnes through the bloud of his ſonne, but alſo he hath confirmed the ſame his promiſe and teſtimonie with an oath, as we may read <hi>Heb. 6.</hi> Therefore <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſheweth, <hi>That they which belieue not the teſtimonie which God giueth of his Sonne commit an horrible offence,</hi> euen this, they make God a lyer. Behold againe what ſweete doctrine, the doctrine of the Church of Rome is, for notwithſtanding the teſtimonie of the three witneſſes from heauen, and the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rite, the water and the bloud, yet they will haue it there ſhould be no certaintie, but a doubt. Humilitie (they ſay) it is no doubt: euen as much as to ſay, it is humilitie to make God a lyer: Is it humilitie to call into queſtion, and doubt the truth of his word &amp; of his oath? for he ſaith, hee that belieueth not God, hath made him a lyer: Is faith and doubting all one? Beloued, we may here learne, that as by doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and diſtruſting the promiſes and teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of God, which he confirmeth with his oth. We offer great iniurie vnto his maieſty, and do highly diſpleaſe him: ſo the more ſtedfaſtly we giue credite to that which hee witneſſeth, the more wee honour him, and doe that which is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18261:31"/> pleaſing in his ſight. In the next wordes he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what witneſſe God giueth of his ſonne, or what is the teſtimonie of all the three witneſſes in heauen, namely, that God hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs eternall life, &amp; this life is in that his ſon. Firſt we ſee the wordes are plaine that God hath freely giuen vnto vs eternall life: this <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſetteth downe as part of the record which God bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. This is greatly to be obſerued, becauſe it expoundeth the ſcriptures. For how wickedly and how impudently doe the Papiſts cauill and peruert the truth, when they ſo ſtifflie affirme, that men obtaine eternall life by their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts? If eternall life be the gift of God, as God himſelfe doth witneſſe ſaith <hi>S. Iohn. How doe men purchaſe it by their owne merites?</hi> And then there is an other part of the teſtimonie which God beareth, and that is, that this life eternall which he giueth vs, is in his ſonne: whereupon he inferreth, that hee that hath the ſonne hath life, and he that hath not the ſon, hath not life becauſe God witneſſeth that hee giueth vnto vs eternall life in Chriſt, it followeth of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie that he which hath Chriſt hath life: for how can the ſonne of God and the true life be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aſunder? Moreouer, ſeing God giueth this happie life onely in his ſonne, he that hath not the ſonne, how is it poſſible that he ſhould haue the life? Here is the ſumme of the Goſpell; that
<pb facs="tcp:18261:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> whatſoeuer ſhal bring vs to life euerlaſting, we haue it whole in Chriſt: God himſelfe doth witnes this. <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Chriſt is of God, made vnto vs wiſdom, righteouſnes, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and redemption, that he which glorieth, ſhould glorie in the Lord. 1. Cor. 1,</hi> Let this teſtimonie of God ſtand, as of neceſſitie it muſt ſtand, and all the whole frame of poperie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth downe. For if all be giuen vnto vs in Chriſt, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth of all thoſe thinges by which the Papiſtes ſay, men get pardon of their ſinnes, and purchaſe life euerlaſting? Where be all the Popes pardons? what becommeth of all their running on pilgrimage to the images of Saintes, to ſeeke life at the hands of dead blocks and ſtones: Well, let this Antichriſtian ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Rome paſſe, and let vs learne from this place to ſeeke eternal life onely in Chriſte, ſeeing God doth beare recorde that eternall life is in his ſonne. They that haue him, neede none other thing to bring them vnto life. They that to obtaine eternall life, will ioyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or other creatures with him, as giuing parte thereof, do diſhonor him, and deny him, and ſo muſt needs miſſe of the true bleſſednes. And now we come to that verſe which I minde to ſtand vpon, becauſe it ſheweth the ende for which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith, he did write theſe thinges. Thus the wordes are: <hi>Theſe thinges haue I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18261:32"/> vnto you that beleeue in the name of that ſonne of God, that ye may knowe that ye haue eternall life, and that yee may beleeue in the name of that ſonne of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may diuide this into two partes, the firſt that all true beleeuers may be aſſured of their ſaluation: the ſecond that they may beleeue. Touching the latter of theſe it may be ſaid: if he wrote to them that did beleeue, and ſo did know that they had life eternall, how could he ſay, <hi>And that ye may belieue?</hi> The anſwere to this is eaſie: no man doth beleeue ſo perfectly, but that his faith may receiue increaſe. But this I will not handle: therefore let vs come againe vnto that former. <hi>That ye may know that ye haue eternall life.</hi> Here are fower things to be noted in this: the firſt is, that it is not vnpoſſible, but men may come to be aſſured that they ſhall be ſaued: the ſecond, that it is not pride, nor arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, or a wicked preſumption for a true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer to aſſure himſelfe that he ſhall be ſaued: the thirde, what way we are to come to this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of our ſaluation: the fourth; &amp; laſt, how we are by degrees to encreaſe this aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Let ſuch then in the firſt place as hold it a thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any man to know he ſhal be ſaued, conſider how flat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary it is which they hold, vnto the word of God: for if it be not poſſible for men to knowe that they ſhal be ſaued, how
<pb facs="tcp:18261:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> could <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſay, <hi>Theſe things haue I written vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that beleeue in the name of the ſon of God, that ye may know that ye haue eternall life?</hi> Ought not this to ſtop the mouthes of all men in this matter? For when he ſaith we may know, ſhall we ſay it is vnpoſſible to know? We grant (ſay ſome) that certaine ſpeciall men might know, and haue aſſurance that they ſhould be ſaued, for it was by ſpeciall reuelation: but it doth not follow thereupon, that the faithfull may come to the knowledge and aſſurance of their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life and ſaluation. Yea euen this cauill alſo is fully anſwered, and taken away by words of the holy Apoſtle: for he writeth to the whole Churches, euen vnto all that haue the true faith in Chriſt: hee ſpeaketh not vnto ſome ſpeciall perſons, but indifferently vnto them all, that they might know they had eternall life. Alſo he doth not ſpeake of any eſpeciall reuelation, but that the knowledge of their ſaluation is by the things which he wrote vnto them. Let all men then (which will not wilfully &amp; wickedly gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay the holy Ghoſt) ſtoope downe &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the truth in this, namely that the faithfull may know that they ſhall haue eternal life. Let this ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd firme and vnremoueable, vnles wee will gaineſay the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Come then to the ſecond point: it is deemed great arrogancy and pride by the Papiſtes, for
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18261:33"/> any man to affirme that hee is ſure hee ſhall be ſaued: yea the Ieſuites cal it da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable falſe illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and preſumption. I wonder how they will anſwere here to <hi>S. Iohn:</hi> woulde he of purpoſe write theſe things, to bring men to a damnable illuſion and wicked arrogancy? Hee ſaith hee wrote theſe things, euen to this end &amp; purpoſe, (for ſo much his words import) that they which beleeue in the name of the ſonne of God, may know they haue eternall life. Why did not the Ieſuites in their annotations ſay ſomewhat vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theſe wordes? Is it not tranſlated amiſſe? Surely they tranſlate it euen thus: <hi>Theſe thinges write I vnto you, that you may know that you haue eternall life, which beleeue in the name of the ſonne of God.</hi> How then? Is there not ſome figuratiue or myſticall ſpeech in theſe words? They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for ſhame ſay ſo. Then it muſt needes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that the Papiſts are proud &amp; arrogant, yea blaſphemous in accuſing <hi>S. Iohn</hi> that he leadeth the faithfull into a damnable illuſion. Is it not ſome one ſpeech, or once vttered by <hi>Saint</hi> Iohn? If it were but one ſpeeche, and once vttered, it were enough, and fully ſufficient to confirme the matter, being vttered by the ſpirite of truth: but in deede <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> vſeth the like ſpeeche more then once, or twiſe. For in the third chapter of this Epiſtle, verſ. 14. he ſaith, <hi>We know we are tranſlated from death to life,
<pb facs="tcp:18261:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> becauſe wee loue the brethren.</hi> And in the ſame Chap. ver. 19. <hi>And by this we know that wee are of the truth, and ſhall perſwade our hearts before him.</hi> Alſo Chap. 4. ver. 13. <hi>By this wee know that we dwell in him, and he in vs, becauſe he hath giuen vs of his ſpirite.</hi> Then let vs proceede vnto the thirde point, which is, that by what way, or by what meanes we may attaine to the aſſurance of our ſaluation. No man needes to doubt, but that <hi>S. Iohn</hi> hath ſhewed the onely waye and means, ſeeing he ſaith, <hi>Theſe things haue I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto you, &amp;c. that yee may know that ye haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</hi> Hee doth not then ſend vp men to ſearch in the ſecret counſel of God, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their names be written in the booke of life: neyther doth he will them to rely vppon ſome ſpeciall reuelation, but wil haue them to know that they haue eternall life, by thoſe thinges which he hath written vnto them. Then are we to ſeeke the way and meanes in that which he hath written. But heere it may be demaunded whether theſe words, <hi>(Theſe things haue I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten)</hi> be to be vnderſtoode of that which goeth before in this Chapter of all that he hath writen in this Epiſtle. Indeede almoſt the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Epiſtle tendeth to that purpoſe, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſhall aduiſedly reade it ouer may eaſily perceiue: but yet it is ſpecially to be referred to that which he hath ſpoken before in this chap.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18261:34"/> touching the full victory that wee haue in Chriſt through faith, and touching the ſix wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which faith is ſupported by. Heere wee are firſt to note how farre they be awry, which woulde haue ſome aſſurance and hope to bee ſaued, and let go the way and meanes by which they ſhoulde attayne that aſſurance. When they heare of a certainty of life, why ſhoulde not wee be perſwaded (ſay they) that God will ſaue vs as well as others? And yet the things which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith, he hath written that men may knowe they haue eternall life, they neyther know, nor care to know: they hold this principle, that it is God onely which doth ſaue men: and vppon this they reſt, not conſidering by what meanes he doth ſaue them: as if a man ſhould ſay that hath grounds, it is God alone that feedeth al fleſh: he only maketh the corne to growe: I care not therefore for plowing or ſowing, if he will feed me, I ſhall be fed, if he will not, what can I helpe it? Will not all men laugh at ſuch folly? Will not euery ſimple man ſay, if he will haue the Lord God to giue him corn for his ſuſtenance, he muſt vſe the means, that is, he muſt plowe, he muſt ſowe, yea reape, and carry into his barnes. Euen ſo God alone bringeth men to eternall life, and giueth the knowledge and certaintie thereof, but he doth it by meanes, and he that will come to it muſt
<pb facs="tcp:18261:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> vſe thoſe meanes. He muſt come to this that <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaith: <hi>Theſe thinges haue I written vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that beleeue, &amp;c. that yee may knowne yee haue eternall life.</hi> Will a man knowe it, or haue it, and yet let paſſe the thinges which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, by which hee is to knowe it, and to haue it. Chriſt willeth the Iewes to ſearch the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, affirming that they doe beare witnes of him. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. He that will knowe Chriſt the ſauiour of the world, in whome the father doth giue vs life eternall, he muſt knowe him by the ſcriptures. The true faith is grounded vpon the witnes which the three witneſſes from heauen, that is the father, the worde, and the holy ghoſte, doe witnes.</p>
            <p>If a man doe not knowe what recorde theſe doe beare, how can he tell what to beleeue? What maner of faith then haue all they which hearken not to the voice &amp; teſtimonie of God, which the holy Apoſtles &amp; Prophets haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in writing: but follow their owne blind imagination? Theſe neuer conſider why God hath reuealed his counſels, or why he ſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, yea and his owne ſonne to publiſh the teſtimony: let vs take heed that we be not of this company, which indeede is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great company, that haue no care to harken what the three which beare record in heauen haue witneſſed. There is an other ſort of men,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18261:35"/> which alſo are much awrie, touching the way and meanes to ſaluation? Theſe doe ſearch the ſcriptures, they reade, they heare, they labour for knowledge, yea, they holde that men may and ought to come to the aſſurance of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and profeſſe that they be ſure thereof themſelues. If you demaunde of them a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all matters, they can from the worde of God ſatisfie you with good reaſons. All this is highly to be commended, whye, or how are they then awrie? They be awrie, which ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and put aſunder thoſe thinges which God hath coupled together. They ſtand ſtrictlie vpon the written worde of God, tell them of putting aſunder the thinges which God hath coupled together, and they will alſo denie it. Yea, they will conſtantly promiſe and profeſſe, that if you can ſhewe them any thing which they put aſunder from that which God hath coupled it vnto, they will be ready to amend their fault. I would that were true: for wee ſhould not then haue ſo many carnall goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers: neither would there be ſo many proude Schiſmatikes. But ſome man may ſay, what be the thinges that God hath coupled together, which ſuch men doe put aſunder? I will tell you. Doth <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſay, that Chriſt came both by water and bloud, not by water alone, but by water and bloud: and yet they will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
<pb facs="tcp:18261:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> theſe two, they will haue remiſſion of their ſinnes, or iuſtification in Chriſt without ſanctification? He that hath Chriſt to bee his righteouſneſſe, muſt needes haue him alſo to bee his ſanctification. A man cannot bee in Chriſt, but hee muſt bee borne of God, he muſt bee a newe creature, he cannot conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſinne, and bee the ſeruant of ſinne, as for that pointe, let men reade and ſtudie wel the 6. Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans.</hi> But let vs proceede further in this matter, as <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> here doth. He ſaith, there be three which beare recorde in heauen, and there bee three which beare record in earth. What will you ſay if they part aſunder theſe ſixe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? What if they leaue out theſe three witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in earth, and ſtand onely vpon the three in heauen? It may be ſaid, is not the teſtimonie of the three witneſſes in heauen ſufficient? May not a man reſt in the teſtimonie of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though there bee none other ioyned? ſurely the teſtimony of God is infallible, and all ſufficient of it ſelfe: but whoſoeuer beleeueth that teſtimonie of God, hath (as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith) the witnes in himſelf: he hath the witnes which is in earth within him, euen the witnes of the ſpirit, of the water, and of the bloud. Where theſe three in earth are not to giue their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, the witnes of the other three in heauen is not beleued, though it ſeeme to be beleeued.
<pb facs="tcp:18261:36"/> As aske a man this queſtion which is caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrie that way, you beleeue the goſpell, I doe, (will he ſay) beleeue it. You are ſure you ſhall haue eternall life: I am ſure thereof (ſaith he) Then demaund further, how come you to that aſſurance, or whereupon doth it reſt? He will anſwere, it reſteth vpon Gods promiſe, I am ſure he can not faile, nor deceiue. That is out of all doubt: but you doe not beleeue it. Yes ſaid he, I doe beleeue it. Then where be the three witneſſes in earth which be in euery one that doth beleeue aright? He that beleeueth, hath the witnes in himſelfe. ver. 10. Where is the bloud, the water, &amp; the ſpirit? I hope (will he ſay further) that they bee within me. But come to the triall: the heart is vnſanctified, the minde is corrupt and vaine, the tongue ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth proude things, vnder the lippes is deceipt, and guile, the handes are full of vniuſt dealing: couetouſnes &amp; pride doe beare ſway. Examine the whole courſe of ſuch a mans life, and you ſhall finde that hee doth not glorifie God. Is the ſpirite of God in the heart ſuch a man? Hath he the power of Chriſt in him euen of the water and the bloud, by which he came? Is he iuſtified, is he ſanctified? No, but as I ſaide before, he doth ſeperate the three witneſſes in earth, from the three in heauen. It is but a vaine arrogancie in him, and a meere illuſion in deed
<pb facs="tcp:18261:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he boaſteth of the certaintie of his ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For he hath nothing but his owne imagination to warrant him that he doth beleeue. It is no maruaile therefore when ſuch doe fall: and to them <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaith: <hi>Let him that thinketh he doth ſtand, take heede that he fall not.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. He doth not ſay, that ſuch as doe ſtand in deede can vtterly fall vnto perdition, but they which are deceiued in their owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, boaſting that they be ſure of ſaluation, and yet haue not in them the three witneſſes in earth. They haue not the firme and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible grounde to reſt vpon, for the certaintie of their faith, and ſo of life euerlaſting. For euen when any ſuch man doth moſt of all glorie that God is his God, and his father: If he would but diſcend into himſelfe, and but a little awake &amp; ſtirre vp his drowſie conſcience, that would tell him that there is no ſuch matter, but that in deede he may expecte the ſeueritie of Gods wrath, his conſcience will tell him, thou haſt a proude heart, thy minde is full of vanitie, thou art defiled continuallie with vile and vncleane luſtes, and with abominable deedes. Thou doeſt delight in ſinful wayes, and takeſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in wicked thinges. God is a moſt ſeuere and a righteous Iudge, he will execute ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon all vngodly men. This vnpleaſant ſong will the conſcience ſing vnto the vnrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18261:37"/> and not that ſweete tune of certaintie, that they ſhall be ſaued. Let vs then omitte theſe which are awrie, and come to that right way and meanes, by which we may attaine to ſo happie an eſtate, as without all deceite or il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, yea, without all arrogancie or vaine preſumption, to knowe that we ſhall be ſaued. We heare that as there is a dead faith, which may eaſilie be knowen, if we were not too too negligent, ſo is there alſo a true and a liuely faith, which we may trie in our ſelues by that which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> here writeth. Which is thus, we muſt not reſt in this alone, what the father, the worde, and the holy Ghoſt doe witnes, as to ſay, I knowe what recorde they beare, or I am out of all doubt that the record is true and infallible which they beare: becauſe it is vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that God ſhould lye: for ſo farre the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall faith doth goe, the dead faith, yea (as I may ſay) the faith of deuils. How then, where is the difference? I muſt haue in me the ſpirite to beare recorde. What ſpirit? The ſpirite of Chriſt, euen the holye Ghoſt; a ſpirite which commeth not alone: but with the water and the bloud by which Chriſt came. He witneſſeth in deede with the efficacie of the death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, which he doth apply both in ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and ſanctification vnto the heartes and conſciences of the belieuers. The voice of this
<pb facs="tcp:18261:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpirite, as it were ſpeaking in the heart of a man and telling him that hee is the childe of God, is moſt certaine and infallible. <hi>The ſame ſpirite</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Paul) beareth witneſſe with our ſpirite, that we be the children of God. Rom. 8.</hi> What will any man ſay, that the holy Ghoſt can deceiue, or can lie? If he witneſſe with the ſpirit of a man that he is the child of God, can it fall out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? Here the Ieſuits and other Papiſts do fret and murmure. The holy Ghoſt (ſay they) can not lye: but how can any man aſſure himſelfe that the holy Ghoſt doth beare record vnto his ſpirit, that he is the childe of God? Doth not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſect of heretikes boaſt that they haue the ſpirit of God? is it not then their priuate fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſpirit which they are led by? For anſwere vnto this, firſt let all men rightly conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Papiſtes doe not flatly gaineſay the holy Apoſtles. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith, it is the ſpirite that beareth record. And <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſayth, that the ſame ſpirite witneſſeth with our ſpirite that we be the ſonnes of God. If it be ſo as they would beare in hand, that a man can not know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath that holy ſpirit, how doth he wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? And touching the reaſon which they vſe (if we may giue the title of a reaſon vnto ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde a ſpeech) marke it well I pray you. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie kinde of heretike, and likewiſe euerie ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie doth boaſt that hee is led by the ſpirite of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18261:38"/> God: therefore no man can tell which is the true ſpirit. If men ſhould trauaile from a farre part of the land towards London, ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the way perfectly &amp; otherſome not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: if they which doe not know it, yet raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſume that they doe, and goe on out of the way; ſhall we affirme thereupon, that the other alſo cannot know it? Were not this verie ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous? And I pray you what other, is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which the Papiſts here vſe? Heretickes are deceiued, which in deede are raſhly led with the ſpirite of Satan, therefore they which are led by the ſpirit of God, can not know for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie whether he be the right ſpirit. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in the 4. Chapter of his Epiſtle verſe 24. ſaith. <hi>He that keepeth his commaundements dwelleth in him, and he in him, and by this we know that he abideth in vs, euen by the ſpirite which he hath giuen vs.</hi> How ſhall any man know that he dwelleth in God, and God in him by his ſpirite that he hath giuen him, if hee can not for certaintie knowe which is the true ſpirite? But how can this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite be knowne for certaintie? He is known by his efficacie, by his working: hee goeth not without the word, hee teſtifieth together with the water &amp; the bloud by which Chriſt came. Hee applieth the mightie power of the death and reſurrection of Chriſt, vnto the heart of the belieuer, both touching remiſſion of ſinnes,
<pb facs="tcp:18261:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſanctification. He that doth beare himſelfe in hand, and boaſt that hee hath the ſpirite of God, and hath not the bloud and the water by which Chriſt came, doth but deceiue himſelfe, and is arrogantly puffed vp, for the three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in earth, the ſpirite, the water, and the bloud, doe goe vnſeperably together. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the power of Chriſt crucified vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and true ſanctification, a man doth know that hee is led by the holy ſpirite of God. <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth ſet forth the ſame matter, but with other words. For when he ſaith, <hi>The ſpirit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe beareth record with our ſpirite, that we be the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es of God Rom. 8. ver. 16.</hi> Hee leaueth him not as a ſpirite at randon, but a little before expreſſeth his operation by which in deede he is knowne. If yee liue after the fleſh (ſaith he) yee ſhall die: but if by the ſpirite you mortifie the deedes of the fleſhe, you ſhall liue. For as many as are led by the ſpirite of God, they are the Sonnes of God. What ſhall we ſay to this? How ſhall a man know that it is the holy ſpirit of God by which he is led? Doth not <hi>S. Paule</hi> tell you that he is a ſpirite which doth mortifie the deedes of the fleſh? There is no ſpirit which doth moritfie, or indeede which can mortifie the deedes of the fleſh, but the ſpirite of Chriſt, who doth it by applying the power of the death of Chriſt. And whereſoeuer he goeth, he hath
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18261:39"/> that worke: ſo that where the deedes of the fleſh are not mortified, there is not the ſpirit of Chriſt. And he that hath not the ſpirit of Chriſt (as it is written) hee is none of his. That man committeth ſinne, and therefore as this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>He hath not ſeene Chriſt nor known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. To come neerer then to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>l, that a man is led by the ſpirite of God, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o aſſured of his ſaluation? What be thoſe deedes of the fleſh, and what is it to mortifie them? All the luſtes of ſinne which are in our nature, all vncleannes, and al the wicked actions which ſpring from the ſame, be called the workes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the deeds of the fleſh. <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaith: The deeds of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe, adulterie, fornication, vncleanneſſe; wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, worſhiping of images, witch craft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, ſectes, enuyings, murthers,, drunkennes, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonies, and ſuch like. <hi>Gal. 5. ver. 19.20.21.</hi> It was not his purpoſe to reckon vp all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he addeth this clauſe, and ſuch like. For there is pride, ambition, vaine-glory, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, periurie, and many other. To mortifie theſe, is not onely to ſuppreſſe the outwarde deedes, but to kill and to roote out the power of them in the heart. As for example, man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proude, the ſpirite of the Lorde doeth kill that euill vice, it changeth the heart and maketh
<pb facs="tcp:18261:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> it humble, and lowlie. Alſo, a man is couetous and earthly minded, the holy ghoſt doth worke in his heart a contempt of worldly thinges, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt in God, and the loue of heauenlie thinges. If he be full of wrath, of rage, of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, and ſuch headdie paſſions, ſo that he is euen as a fierce and ſauage beaſt by nature, the ſpirite of grace doth ſubdue and roote out theſe, and make him gentle and meeke as a lambe. Where vncleane luſtes of whoredome and fornication doe burne, and boile in the heart, the heauenlie ſpirit doeth quench them, and maketh the minde chaſte and pure. What ſhould I ſtand to repeate many particulars, you may by theſe ſee what it is in all the reſt? This is that which Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Nicodemus: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man he borne againe, he cannot ſee the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> This is it which the holie Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul,</hi> calleth the putting off the olde man, and putting on the newe. Yea, this is that which the ſcripture calleth repentance. Can any man haue this worke in him, &amp; not knowe aſſuredly that he is led by the ſpirite of God. The papiſtes in deede doe vtterly condemne this; becauſe they be vtterly voide of it, and can not tell what it is. For how can they which denie &amp; condemne the true doctrine of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation in Chriſt, be partakers of the ſpirite which doth aſſure the faithfull of eternall life?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:40"/>
            <p>But yet they haue a further obiection, and which in deede they deeme to be vnanſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let it be (ſay they) that a man doth knowe he hath the ſpirite of God, that he is regener<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> and is in the ſtate of grace, yet is he ſure he ſhal ſtand to the end, and not looſe that ſpirite and fall from grace, or is he ſure he ſhall not ſinne? Is not this great preſumption? Verily it were great preſumption, according to the Popiſh doctrine, for any man to aſſure himſelfe that he ſhall ſtand to the ende: for they teach that a man ſtandeth by free will. So I graunt it were fowle preſumption for any man to preſume vpon his owne ſtrength: but it is no preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a man to reſt vppon the infallible cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Gods promiſe, &amp; the teſtimonie of the holy ſpirite: for when the Apoſtle ſaith, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite himſelfe witneſſeth with our ſpirit that we be the ſonnes of God: doth he witneſſe, that we are, and doth he not witneſſe that we ſhall be ſo, euen to the end? Can a man to day bee the childe of God, and to morrow not? Moreouer, there is no godly man which ſaith, he is ſure he ſhall not ſinne: for all men ſinne dayly. But the regenerate doe know that through the grace of God, they ſhall not ſo ſinne as to fall quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from Chriſt, or to haue the life of GOD (whereof they are made partakers in the newe birth) vtterly extinguiſhed in them. Touching
<pb facs="tcp:18261:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> this pointe <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in Chapter 3. of his Epiſtle <hi>verſe</hi> 9. ſaith, <hi>Whoſoeuer is borne of God, ſinneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for his ſeede remaineth in him, and he can not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe he is borne of God.</hi> What can all the Papiſtes in the world ſay vnto this? <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith not that ſome of thoſe which are borne of God doe ſtand to the end, but he ſaith, <hi>Whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not.</hi> Then is it certaine that he which doth know hee is borne of God, and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by his ſpirite, doth alſo know that hee ſhall not fall vnto deſtruction. And for this hee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth a reaſon, namely, that the ſeede of God remaineth in him. The regenerating grace is neuer loſt, if the ſeede of God remaine ſtill in him that is borne of God, yea euen when hee doth by infirmitie (as <hi>Dauid</hi> did) fall into ſome grieuous ſinnes. Alſo he ſaith, that ſuch a one can not ſinne, this ſeemeth an heard ſaying. Is there any man beyond whoſe power it is for to ſinne? Is it ſo heard a matter for a man to doe wickedly, if he will endeuour? Wee muſt not take it that he which is borne of God will euer endeuour for to commit ſinne. No, the grace of God doth ſtill ſo guide him, that he doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to pleaſe God: and though by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and frailtie hee doe after goe awrie and tranſgreſſe, yet can he not fall from God: hee can not vtterly looſe his new birth. The reaſon which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> rendreth is, becauſe he is borne
<pb facs="tcp:18261:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> of God. God is immortall: the ſeed of God by which his children are regenerate is immor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> as it is written, 1. <hi>Pet. 1. The life of God begin in them is immortall:</hi> how then can it be extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed? or how can he that is borne of God fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vnto perdition? Let all men then knowe, that where there is the witnes of the ſpirite, of the water, and the bloud, there is the certainty of ſaluation: according as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſayth, <hi>Theſe thinges haue I written vnto you that beleeue in the name of the ſonne of God, that ye may know that ye haue eternall life, and that yee may beleeue in the name of the ſonne of God.</hi> There are yet another ſort of men, I cannot tell what I ſhould tearme them, that are confuted by this place: they hold that a man for the triall of his faith, whether it be liuely or a dead faith, is not to looke vppon the fruites thereof. It is enough (ſay they) that a man doe beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt: what ſhoulde hee, or what can hee examine further? Faith is Faith. Beleeue, and thou ſhalt bee ſaued. Theſe men doe quite aboliſh, and that moſt wickedly and profanely, the teſtimony of the three witneſſes in earth. They bring in Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme and all carnall liberty. Let not the wiſe harken vnto them, but looke for the teſtimony of the ſpirite, of the water, &amp; of the bloud with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, if they will be aſſured that their faith is the true faith, &amp; that they ſhal come to life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.
<pb facs="tcp:18261:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> And nowe let vs come to the laſt poynt, which is that the faithfull are by degrees to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe this certainty of their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To make an entrance into this matter, it is good for vs to conſider that the ſpirituall birth is compared and likened to the naturall birth: for as in the naturall birth there is firſt brought forth a little weake babe, which hath life, and doth in tyme by degrees, euen by little &amp; little grow vp vnto mans eſtate, ſo in the ſpirituall birth, ſuch as be borne againe in Chriſt, they be firſt as little babes, they haue indeede the life of GOD in them, but they be maruelous weake. Reade touching this, what <hi>S. Peter</hi> writeth in his firſt Epiſtle, in the beginning of the ſecond Chap. how he doth will theſe new borne babes to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet the ſincere milk of the word, that they may grow thereby. And likewiſe what <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Cor. 1. Epiſt. Chap. 4.</hi> Then as in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall thinges, as a man groweth vp in yeeres, ſo he groweth to a riper knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in matters of this worlde: ſo they that grow vp in Chriſt, come to more and more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance that they be led by the Sprite of God, and that they ſhall be ſaued. Moſt true it is alſo; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no man can deny, that in the naturall things men do grow vp from babes to mans eſtate by food and ſuſtenance, they grow alſo in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; vnderſtanding by practiſe &amp; meanes.
<pb facs="tcp:18261:42"/> The ſame is to be ſaide of the babes in Chriſt: they cannot growe vp without the Spirituall food, they cannot come to more aſſured know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by the means which God hath ordained, and that is it which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> here leadeth vnto, when he ſaith, <hi>Theſe thinges haue I written vnto you, &amp;c. that ye may know that ye haue eternall life.</hi> Well then, ſeeing wee muſt grow vp vnto this happy aſſurance by meanes, let vs in ſome fewe particulars conſider howe: firſt ſeeing the word of GOD is the ſincere milke by which we are to be nouriſhed, and to grow vp, it is our part, as the ſame Apoſtle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, to couet the ſame. <hi>1. Pet. 2.2.</hi> Wee doe all know this, that when a childe is borne, if it be aliue and in health, howe much it doth couet the mothers breaſt, and how ſweete the milke is vnto it: in like manner, when a man is borne of God in the new and heauenly birth, he hath a vehement deſire and longing after Gods word, it is maruellous ſweete and delectable vnto him. And queſtionles, all ſuch as care not, nor labor not to know the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly oracles, are void of the ſpiritual life: they be like vnto thoſe children which are borne dead, which care not for the mothers breaſt. We muſt labour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by reading and by hearing the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, by meditation &amp; earneſt prayer to come to the true vnderſtanding and right vſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:18261:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſacred word of God. Marke further what <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> then teacheth, how men ſhall attaine to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſaluation. He willeth to giue all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to miniſter in our faith vertue, in vertue knowledge, in knowledge temperance, in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance patience, in patience godlines, in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines brotherly kindnes, in brotherly kindnes loue: for if theſe things be in you and abound, they ſhall make you that yee neyther ſhall be idle nor vnfruitefull in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: but hee that lacketh theſe things is blinde, and cannot ſee farre off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old ſinnes. <hi>2, Pet. 1. ver. 5.6.7.8.9.</hi> Heere is the way preſcribed, and by this men ſhall attaine to the certainty of their ſaluation, which <hi>S. Pet.</hi> there expreſſeth in <hi>verſe 10.</hi> and <hi>11.</hi> after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Wherefore brethren giue the more diligence, to make your calling and election ſure: for if you doe ſuch things you ſhal neuer fal.</hi> And by this meanes an entrance ſhall be miniſtred vnto you abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly into the euerlaſting Kingdome of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. What can be ſpoken more clearly for the certainty of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? and that by meanes &amp; degrees men riſe vp vnto it? Doth he not teach that by thoſe things men ſhal make their calling and election ſure? What is that? but that they ſhall thereby know aſſuredly that GOD hath called them and
<pb facs="tcp:18261:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> choſen them vnto eternall life. For doing thoſe thinges, he pronounceth that they ſhall neuer fal. What is it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which maketh men to doubt that they ſhall not be ſaued? Is it not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſinne which is in them? Is it not that their heart is full of vncleane vices, and that the holie vertues are wanting? Now where the vices haue their full power, and doe raigne, there is a whole doubting, and worthilie: for men may aſſure themſelues that in ſuch an eſtate, they cannot be ſaued. Then where the worke of the ſpirite is begunne, ſo that the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſomewhat ſuppreſſed, and the vertues beginne to budde and growe vp, there ariſeth ſome comforte and aſſurance, there the ſpirite, the water, and the bloud beginne to beare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde. This is a true recorde, but yet it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not ſo cleare, becauſe the remnants of ſinne are verie ſtrong and plenteous, and the vertues are, as I may ſay, tender and weake. Now, as knowledge, and faith, and the power of the ſpirite increaſeth, as the deedes of the fleſh are more and more mortified and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, ſo the teſtimonie of the ſpirite, of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and of the bloud, is more cleare and ſtrong. The more godly the heart &amp; the minde grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the more aſſurance we haue that we ſhall be ſaued. Many ſay, O what a bleſſed thing it is, if a man attaine to the knowledge and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb facs="tcp:18261:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> of this ſaluation? How willingly will that man loue and obey God? how chearefullie wil he beare all troubles, and afflictions? I feele ſometime great ioye, and aſſurance of Gods loue towardes me: but through mine owne negligence, I haue ſo many ſinnes, as that they take away my comforte, and make me doubt. Then conſider what waye we are to ouercome ſuch doubtes, and to come to that happie and bleſſed aſſurance. Mortifie the deedes of the fleſhe by the ſpirite. What is it that depriueth thee of this happie eſtate, and maketh thee to doubte? Is it not through the want of the cleere teſtimonie in thee, of the three which beare recorde in earth? Thou haſt many ſinnes in thee, which thou ſeeſt not, and it may be, very great ones, as loftines of minde, vaine-glorie, couetouſneſſe, ſelfe-loue, vanitie of minde, contempt of ſpirituall thinges, and ſuch like. Yea, further it may be, that ſundrie thinges which thou deemeſt in thy ſelfe to be vertues, examine them wel by the light of Gods worde, and thou ſhalt finde them to be vices. So long as it is thus, there will be doubting: for where is the teſtimonie of the ſpirite with the water and the bloud? Mortifie the vices by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, vſe all diligence with feruent prayer, and all other good meanes, and giue not ouer, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou ſeemeſt ſometimes to labour in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18261:44"/> vaine: for in continuance of time, thou ſhalt gaine much, and great peace ſhall ariſe in thy conſc ence, and the ſame ſpringing more and more, as thou ſhalt purge it from dead workes. O beloued, this is the way of ſaluation, enter into it, and giue not ouer, it is worth the labour. The Lorde bleſſe vs, that we may be founde conſtant euen to the ende. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE THIRDE Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hebrewes. 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>16</bibl> Let there be no fornicator or prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as Eſau, which for one portion of meate, ſould his birthright.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>17</bibl> For ye knowe that afterward, when he would haue inherited the bleſſing, he was reiected: for he found no place for repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, though he ſought it with teares.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll wiſe men do account it a friendlie parte, when any doe forewarne and ſhewe vnto them, how they may preuent and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chue ſome great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that was comming towardes them. I truſt therefore, that you will be the more attentiue to this ſcripture, in which
<pb facs="tcp:18261:45"/> not a mortall man, but the holy ghoſt, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of wiſedome and trueth, doth ſet before vs a moſt horrible daunger, and ſuch, as if we fall into it, we are vtterly vndone for euer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all recouery. Now, that I may make it the more plaine and eaſie vnto you to beholde, we may deuide it into three partes. The firſt is, a precept, or warning giuen vnto vs, to take heed there be no prophane perſon. It is in theſe wordes: <hi>Let there be no fornicator, or prophane perſon.</hi> I doe omitte to ſpeake of the fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who is here ioyned with the prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The ſecond parte propoundeth an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the facte, whereby he ſheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be prophane, that wee may ſee what the ſinne of prophaneſſe is, or whom the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calleth prophane men: and it is in theſe wordes, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> who for one portion of meate ſould his birthright. The third and laſt ſetteth forth the ſeueritie of Gods iudgement and wrath vpon him, which is the horrible daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that I ſpake of, into which they fall with him that followe <hi>Eſau</hi> in prophaneſſe. The wordes be theſe: <hi>For ye knowe that afterwarde alſo, when hee would haue inherited the bleſſing hee was reiected, for he found no place for repentance, though he ſought it with teares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come then to the precept, <hi>Let there bee no prophane perſon.</hi> It may be demanded whether
<pb facs="tcp:18261:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> this bee giuen to euery priuate and particular man, or to the Paſtors &amp; guides of the flocke, or to both? Doubtleſſe to both. For as the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards are to watch ouer the whole flocke, to teach, to exhort, to admoniſh &amp; to rebuke euen euery particular man, as need ſhall require: ſo is euerie priuate man to haue a ſingular and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care to take heede to himſelfe, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not prophane, otherwiſe, what ſhall all the diligence of the teachers preuaile? Yea, moreouer all men are inioyned to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider one another, to prouoke vnto loue &amp; good workes, and to exhorte one another, as we reade in the tenth Chapter of this Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes, ver, 24.25. For hee that ſhall ſee his brother, his friende, his neighbour, or familiar acquaintance grow prophane and ſo running into that daunger of Gods heauie diſpleaſure,</hi> here ſet forth in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſhall not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued therewith, nor touched with care and loue to admoniſh him, it argueth that hee is deeply tainted with prophaneſſe himſelfe. He loueth not God, hee loueth not aright his owne ſoule, that careth not whither other men walke. Therefore let the Paſtors vſe all their diligence to looke to their flock, that prophaneſſe creepe not in among them. Let euery man watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his owne heart and conſcience, and take heede to himſelfe, yea let him not neglect his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18261:46"/> neighbour, for this is an vndoubted thing, that Satan laboureth to make men prophane, and preuaileth much. To be prophane is a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable thing, as it doth appeare by the ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gods diſpleaſure &amp; indignation againſt it, expreſſed in the laſt part of this text: but the moſt men doe not know what it is. They doe vnderſtand that it is taken in very euill part whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay one is prophane, they know it is a ſore accuſation, but yet they can not tell the nature of the ſinne, or wherein prophaneſſe doeth conſiſt. In the ſeconde place therefore, here i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an example ſet down of a very prophane man, and what his prophaneſſe was. So that from hence wee may learne what the ſinne is, which the holy ghoſt warneth vs to take heede of. The man propounded for an example vnto vs is <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> the elder ſonne of <hi>Iſaake</hi> the great Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke. Wee are then warned to take heede, that we be not like prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> for if we be, wee are ſure to drinke of the ſame cup that hee did: for God is no reſpecter of perſons, if he ſpared not him, he will not ſpare thee, if thou be found like him, but wherin did he ſhew himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane? He ſolde his birth right for one portion of meate. Herein lyeth the matter, this needeth expoſition: for by this wee ſhall ſee what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe is. <hi>God called Abraham from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r of the Chaldeans, he made his couenant with him, that
<pb facs="tcp:18261:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> he would bee his God and the God of his ſeede: and alſo that in his ſeede all the nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed.</hi> In this is included that Chriſt the Sauiour of the worlde ſhoulde come of his ſeede. <hi>Abraham</hi> begate <hi>Iſaake</hi> of <hi>Sarah.</hi> And vnto <hi>Iſaake</hi> by the expreſſe commaundement of God, willing <hi>Abraham</hi> to caſt out the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman and her ſonne, the bleſſing came. For in that place he ſaith, <hi>In Iſaake ſhall thy ſeede be called. Gen. 21. ver. 12. Abraham</hi> therefore paſſed this bleſſing ouer, not vnto <hi>Iſmael</hi> his elder ſonne, but vnto his ſonne <hi>Iſaake. Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing olde, he tooke an oth of his ſeruant that he ſhould goe into the land of his Natiuitie, and from thence take a wife for his ſonne <hi>Iſaake.</hi> He did bring <hi>Rebecca,</hi> whom <hi>Iſaake</hi> tooke to wife, ſhe was married vnto him twentie yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe had any childe. For it is written that <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaake</hi> was fortie yeares olde when he married, <hi>Gen, 25. ver. 20.</hi> And he was threeſcore yeares of age, when <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> were borne, as we reade in the ſame Chapter verſe 26. For <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca</hi> being all that while barren, <hi>Iſaake</hi> praied to God for her, and the Lord heard him, and ſhee conceiued, and the children ſtraue in her wombe, whereat ſhee was troubled, and went to enquire of the Lorde touching the ſame. Where anſwere was made vnto her by God, two nations be in thy wombe, and two peoples
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18261:47"/> ſhall be ſeperated from thy wombe, the one people ſhall be greater then the other people, and the greater ſhall ſerue the leſſer. <hi>Eſau</hi> was the firſt borne, as we reade in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and ſo the birthright, euen the heauenly bleſſing, that God ſhould be his God, and Chriſt to come of his ſeede, was by the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie courſe of nature, to be conueyed vnto him. This bleſſing could bee paſſed ouer but vnto one of the two ſonnes, and <hi>Eſau</hi> was the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by birth. But then <hi>Moſes</hi> doeth proceede and ſhewerh how prophane this <hi>Eſau</hi> was. He ſaith, that when they were growen vp, <hi>Eſau</hi> followed hunting, &amp; <hi>Iaacob</hi> was a plaine man, and dwelt in tents. He dwelt with cattel, that was the husbandry and trade of life which he followed. Alſo, that which we tranſlate, a plaine man, is in the Hebrewe, a man of ſimplicitie, integritie, vprightnes, ſinceritie, or ſome dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſuch an one was <hi>Iaacob. Eſau</hi> came wearie out of the fielde, and <hi>Iaakob</hi> had made pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and he requeſted that he would giue him ſome of them. <hi>Iaacob</hi> anſwereth, ſell me then thy birthright. <hi>Eſau</hi> ſaide, behold, I am readie to die, and what is the birthright to me? Then <hi>Iaakob</hi> ſaide, ſweare vnto me, and hee ſware vnto him, and ſould his birthright to <hi>Iaakob.</hi> And when <hi>Iaakob</hi> had giuen him bread, and pottage, hee eate, and drunke, roſe vp, and
<pb facs="tcp:18261:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> went his way, and ſet light by, or diſpiſed the birthright.</p>
            <p>Now may you perceiue wherein his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe lay, which God is ſo highly offended withall, that he ſetteth ſo light by the heauenly bleſſing, as that he would ſell it for a meſſe of pottage. <hi>Iſaake</hi> had inſtructed them touching the promiſe: <hi>Eſau</hi> did knowe that the Sauiour of the worlde was promiſed with that birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: hee is ſo earthly minded, for this world, and for his belly, that he preferreth a little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie before it. In a worde, he made little account of ſpirituall graces and heauenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in Chriſt, or of that couenant which God had made with his grandfather <hi>Abraham,</hi> who liued vntill he was fifteene yeeres olde, ſo olde I ſay, was <hi>Eſau</hi> when <hi>Abraham dyed.</hi> That co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant being now renewed with <hi>Iſaake</hi> his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that heauenlie bleſſing and grace of God, in which <hi>Iſaake</hi> moſt reioyced, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie purpoſed in deede to conuey it ouer vnto <hi>Eſau,</hi> did hee nothing eſteeeme. Hee was then prophane, becauſe hee did eſteeme and loue as a carnall worldling, the baſe and tranſitorie thinges of this worlde, more then the heauenly promiſe and bleſſing of GOD. You may now diſcerne what the ſinne of prophaneneſſe is. And ſo what it is which the holy Ghoſt warneth vs to beware of,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18261:48"/> when he ſaith, <hi>Let there be no prophane perſon as Eſau.</hi> But ſome man may obiecte, howe can there be any like <hi>Eſawe,</hi> is there any birthright now, or any ſuch couenant and promiſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Chriſt to come? If not, how can this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Eſau</hi> be applied to vs, can any be like him, when there is not the matter, wherein they may bee like? I graunt that there is no birthright now, as there was betweene <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> or couenant touching Chriſt to come of their ſeede: but yet the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t made with <hi>Abraham</hi> belongeth vnto vs, as to haue this birthright, to become the ſonnes of the moſt high GOD through Chriſt the bleſſed ſeede, to be heires of life euerlaſting. This is it which is ſet before vs, and all ſuch as doe ſet their hearts vpon carnall pleaſures, honors and riches of this world, louing them, and ſeeking after them, more then after this heauenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and grace of God in Chriſt, delighting more in bellie-cheere, then in the Goſpell, which is the glad tidings of ſaluation, what are they but prophane perſons, euen like <hi>Eſawe,</hi> which made more account of one portion of meate, then of his birthright? Yea, but <hi>Eſau</hi> ſould his birthright for a trifle. May ſome man obiecte and ſay, ſurely all the luſtes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſinne, which are but for a ſeaſon: all the riches and honors of this worlde which are
<pb facs="tcp:18261:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> tranſitorie, vpon which men ſet their heartes, and are drowned in them, are but trifles, yea euen a meſſe of pottage in compariſon of the heauenly birthright offred in the goſpel, which manie ſet light by.</p>
            <p>And if the great thinges of this world might ſomewhat excuſe, as to ſay, men are not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane as to ſell the kingdome of heauen for a matter of nothing: yet there be many which their owne conſcience doe tell them, if they would examine it, that they more ſet by a paire of olde ſhooes, then by the glorious Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. The rich treaſures of the kingdome of GOD are opened and offred in the ſame, euen as goodly pearles of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable value: but to ſuch worldly minded me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be powred out as before ſwine, which treade them vnder their feete, they ſet light by them, their noſes muſt into the trough to their ſwil, and vnto the porrage pot with <hi>Eſau.</hi> Is not this a great prophaneſſe? Is not this a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful blindnes that men ſhould diſcerne no more of ſpirituall and heauenly thinges, then ſwine doe of pearles, which they will treade in the mire? And yet Chriſt ſpeaketh of ſome that are more prophane, whom he calleth dogges: a dogge is counted a moſt profane thing: and as our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Caſt not pearles before ſwine, becauſe they still treade them vnder their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18261:49"/> feete:</hi> ſo he ſaith, <hi>Giue not holy thinges to dogs, leaſt they turne againe and all to rent you.</hi> The profane dogge goeth further then the profane ſwine: for the ſwine is quyet and will but treade the heauenly pearles vnder his feete, whereas the dogge doth turne againe, bite and teare thoſe which giue holy thinges vnto them. Theſe be ſuch as doe reproach, raile vpon, and perſecute them that bring the Goſpell. Thus may you ſee in what account the profane perſons like <hi>Eſau</hi> be in before God and his Angels, when Chriſt calleth them dogges and ſwine, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. The holy Ghoſt (as you ſee) warneth that there be no profane perſon like <hi>Eſau:</hi> as who ſay. It is an horrible thinge for any one ſuch to be found in the Church: and yet alas, now they ſwarme euery where: how many townes and villages may a man come to in this land, where he ſhall ſcarce finde two or three which zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly imbrace the Goſpell? They be honeſt men, they follow their worldly buſines, which in it ſelfe indeede is not vnhoneſt: no more was it for <hi>Eſau</hi> to eate a meſſe of pottage when he was hungry. But in the meane time together with their honeſt dealing, they doe as <hi>Eſau</hi> for a meſſe of pottage ſel their birth-right, becauſe they loue and ſeeke their belly, and the things of this preſent world, more then the honour &amp; high dignity of the heauenly birth and ſonnes
<pb facs="tcp:18261:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> of God. Is not this a moſt lamentable caſe, that men ſhould be ſo profane? Now to the thirde part, which ſetteth forth the heauy iudgement of God vpon <hi>Eſau,</hi> &amp; ſo in him, euen as it were in a table, painteth out vnto vs in liuely colours what fore vengeance abideth for all ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane worldlings as ſell their birth-right, that is, to fil their belly with ſome dainties for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, ſet light by the grace of God. The words are thus, <hi>For ye know that afterward when he would haue inherited the bleſſing, hee was reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and found no place of repentance, though hee ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght it with teares.</hi> The ſumme of the matter is as you ſee, that wheras <hi>Eſau</hi> before had with a profane minde ſet ſo light by the birth-right, that he ſold it for a trifle; now afterward, when he was deſirous to inherite the bleſſing of that birth-right, he was reiected: yea he cryed and wept to obtaine it, and miſſed thereof: he was then as a profane man reiected and coſt off vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to condemnation. This is the heauy iudgement of God eſpecially, that though he did eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with teares ſeeke to haue that bleſſing and heauenly grace, yet was he caſt off. So it is then, that theſe profane men, which ſet ſo light by the grace of God offred in the Goſpell, may be touched in conſcience, and deſire, when they are to depart out of this worlde, that they might haue the dignitie of the ſonnes of God: yea they may
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18261:50"/> with teares and bitter crying craue it, and yet be reiected. Is not here then a wonderful great and fearefull daunger, which we are warned to take heede of? And being indeed ſo great, yet men doe not knowe that there is any daunger, but imagining God will heare them, how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanely ſoeuer they haue liued. But to open the matter, we muſt haue recourſe vnto the hiſtory ſet downe by <hi>Moſes, Geneſ. 27. Iſaake</hi> was old and his ſight failed him: and he called <hi>Eſau</hi> his elder ſonne, and willed him to take his bow &amp; quiuer, and to goe hunt ſome veniſon, and to make him ſuch meate as hee knew hee loued: then to bring it to him, that he might eate of it, and bleſſe him: <hi>Iſaake</hi> (as I told you before) had a full and reſolute purpoſe to beſtowe and to conuey ouer the heauenly bleſſing vnto <hi>Eſau.</hi> And indeede this <hi>Eſau</hi> made now full account that he ſhould haue it: for what now ſhould let? See what hope of felicity the worldly profane: men are ſometime led into, from which when they fall, it is the more grieuous vnto them. When a man is in exceeding great heate and ready to fainte with thirſt, and hath a cuppe of cold drinke in his hand, euen lifting it vp to his mouth, and then it is plucked from him, what a griefe is it? as the Poets haue fayned, that ſome of the paines of hell be in ſuch manner: ſo <hi>Eſau</hi> here co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, euen ready to haue the bleſſing
<pb facs="tcp:18261:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> put into his hands: but when he looketh aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly to haue it, it is gone: for ſee, <hi>Rebecca</hi> who loued <hi>Iaakob,</hi> and worthily, heard when this was ſpoken to <hi>Eſau:</hi> ſhe willeth <hi>Iaakob</hi> to go to the flocke, to fetch her two good kiddes, and ſhe made ſuch meat with them as <hi>Iſaak</hi> loued: ſhe put the garment of <hi>Eſau</hi> vppon <hi>Iaakob,</hi> ſhe put the skinnes of the kiddes vppon his handes and vppon the bare of his necke, becauſe <hi>Eſau</hi> was heary: ſhe put the meat in his hand, and ſo <hi>Iaakob</hi> went in to his father, and ſaid he was <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau:</hi> he felt him, becauſe he ſaid, the voyce was the voyce of <hi>Iaakob,</hi> but the handes were the hands of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſo he bleſſed him. When he was gone forth, then came <hi>Eſau</hi> with the meat which he had prepared, and craued the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: <hi>Iſaak</hi> demanded who he was, and he told him that he was <hi>Eſau.</hi> Then was <hi>Iſaak</hi> aſtonied and affraid exceedingly, and ſhewed him how his brother had come by fraude, and taken it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: he told him that he had bleſſed <hi>Iaakob,</hi> &amp; that he muſt be bleſſed. Then did <hi>Eſau</hi> cry out with a great &amp; an exceeding bitter cry, crauing that he might be bleſſed. And (as we reade af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in that Chapter, <hi>He lift vp his voyce and wept:</hi> But yet <hi>Iſaake</hi> doth not alter, there is no place for repentance; <hi>Iſaake</hi> ſaw now that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was of God, &amp; ſo confirmed it vnto <hi>Iaakob,</hi> and ſo <hi>Eſau</hi> was reiected. Thus may you briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18261:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſee how the matter ſtood: but now it ſhall not be impertinent, to open the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more at large in all theſe foure perſons, <hi>Iſaak Rebecca, Iaakob,</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi> Firſt touching <hi>Iſaake,</hi> it is a thing that may bee wondred at, how he ſhould be ſo blinded with naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that he could not eſpie the prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Eſau,</hi> but loued him better then he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Iaakob,</hi> who was an exceeding godlie, and a verie reuerend holy man. It is more to be wondred at, that he was ſo caried in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for a worldly commoditie: for <hi>Moſes chap. 25.</hi> noteth the cauſe expreſſely, why <hi>Iſaak</hi> loued <hi>Eſau,</hi> euen becauſe the veniſon was in his mouth. He was led here-vnto by the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that meate which <hi>Eſau</hi> hunted. But in deede, it is moſt of all to be wondred at, that he was ſo farre blinded in his natural affection, as that he would, contrary to the oracle of God, <hi>Chap. 25.</hi> which ſaid, the greater ſhoulde ſerue the leſſer, ſeeke to deriue the bleſſing vnto <hi>Eſau,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we may ſee, that the holy Patriarkes were not without their frailties &amp; imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they had not the fleſh ſo farre mortified in them, but that the remnantes thereof did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, and now and then beare a great ſtroke. It was by grace and free pardon of their ſinnes, that they were ſaued. Looke vpon <hi>Lot,</hi> looke
<pb facs="tcp:18261:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> vpon <hi>Ahraham</hi> the father of the faithfull, looke vpon <hi>Dauid,</hi> and you ſhall finde the ſame. As wee may hereby on the one ſide take comfort, when we beholde our owne corruption, which doth ſo often leade vs awrie: ſo on the other ſide it ought to ſhake of all ſecuritie, and ſtirre vs vp to prayer and watching, leaſt we be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by our corrupt nature, and fall into thoſe things which diſhonour God, and prouoke him to plague vs. For thus we may reaſon, if the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Patriarke <hi>Iſaake,</hi> a man ſo highly repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the ſpirite of God, had notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch corruption of the fleſh remaining in him, which did ſo daungerouſly blind him, and carrie him awrie: what ſhall become of vs, if God doe not by his grace and holy ſpirite pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent vs, which are full of the ſtrong remnantes of ſo many noyſome luſtes in the fleſh? Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we fall, if we bee but euen a little left vnto our ſelues? Are not we in daunger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſo deepe as neuer to riſe againe? Alſo, if ſo holy a man as <hi>Iſaake</hi> was blinded in his ſonne with naturall affection, and for ſo ſmall a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie? How are other to feare that they bee not alſo blinded in their children, when they bee prophane, and ſo doe not correct, nor by wholſome admonition withdraw them from the way of perdition? Now touching <hi>Rebecca,</hi> ſhe loued her ſonne <hi>Iaacob,</hi> ſhee would haue
<pb facs="tcp:18261:52"/> the bleſſing to come vpon him. Doubtleſſe ſhe had good cauſe ſo to doe: for <hi>Iaacob</hi> was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, and the Oracle of God was for him. Thus farre <hi>Rebecca</hi> was right: but now that ſhe deuiſeth a ſleight to deceiue <hi>Iſaake,</hi> and ſendeth <hi>Iaacob</hi> her ſonne with a lye vnto him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in appeareth her frailtie, ſhee can not bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed. She had indeede as I ſaid before, the Oracle on her ſide, before the children were borne, God preferred the yonger, this ſhee did belieue, but now to bring it to paſſe, ſhee will helpe God. She heard <hi>Iſaake</hi> tell <hi>Eſau</hi> that hee would bleſſe him, and ſhee ſeeth no way how this ſhould be altered but by a cunning deuice. We may behold the like in <hi>Sarah</hi> the mother of the faithfull. God made his couenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> that in his ſeede all the nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, ſhee belieued this promiſe, but ſhee began to wax olde, ſhe grew toward foureſcore, ſhee had beene barren all her youth, it ſeemed a difficult matter how it ſhould be brought to paſſe, therefore ſhe doth deuiſe how to further it. She had an handmaide named <hi>Hagar,</hi> ſhee giueth her vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> that he might haue a childe by her. This turned to her owne griefe, for when <hi>Hagar</hi> ſaw ſhee had conceiued, ſhee became ſo proud that ſhe deſpiſed <hi>Sarah.</hi> Surely, when our inuentions are brought in to further the workes of God, they
<pb facs="tcp:18261:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> doe often times turne to our griefe, although this deuiſe of <hi>Rebecca</hi> tooke effect. And nowe touching <hi>Iaacob</hi> that ſo much deſired the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing euen as an holye man that preferred hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things before earthly, how can he bee excuſed in this his deede, that he muſt faine and lye? There doth remaine <hi>Eſau</hi> now, what fault can be found in his doing touching this action? He obeyeth his father, who willed him to goe hunt him ſome veneſon, hee prepareth it and bringeth it, and craueth of his father to bleſſe him. <hi>Iſaake</hi> as we haue ſeene was led awrie by naturall affection? when hee minded to bleſſe <hi>Eſau.</hi> Alſo <hi>Rebecca,</hi> ſhee had her fault in that ſhe deuiſed ſuch a ſleight to deceiue <hi>Iſaake,</hi> and ſo to haue him bleſſe <hi>Iaacob,</hi> when hee thought hee had bleſſed <hi>Eſau. Iaacob</hi> was in the ſame fault with his mother. Onely <hi>Eſau</hi> at this time dealeth ſo as he cannot in this thing be blamed. The other three are deare to God, and <hi>Eſau</hi> is reiected. What may wee note in this? Surely that it is not the outward doing of ſome one action, or of a few which declare a man to bee righteous before God, for this prophane man can not bee blamed here in his one outwarde deede. And ſo let men knowe that all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and prophane diſpiſers of holy things, doe not that which is acceptable before God, when they make a glorious ſhewe of ſome goodly
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18261:53"/> deedes: for before the fruite can be good, the tree muſt be good: before the actions can bee ſuch as ſhall pleaſe God, the heart and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence within muſt be ſincere, euen purged from prophaneſſe and filthie vncleaneſſe.</p>
            <p>What is all the Phariſaicall almes, faſting, and prayer of hypocrites? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. What if a man ſhould giue all his goods to the poore, and haue not loue. <hi>1. Cor. 13.</hi> Againe, we may marke on the other ſide, how, where the heart is ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified with a liuely faith, wher there is the true loue of God, &amp; the thankefull imbracing of his ſpirituall bleſſings, there the particular errors, ſlippes and defects doe not caſt ſuch out of the fauour of God, or make them not to bee holy and righteous men. Then from hence let vs be wiſe in diſcerning: <hi>Eſau</hi> was not an holy man for his vpright cariage in one action? Neither were <hi>Iſaake, Rebecca</hi> and <hi>Iaacob</hi> vnholie for ſwaruing in ſome particulars. At this day you ſhall beholde in thoſe, which from their heart loue and imbrace the Goſpell, ſundrie imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, take euen the beſt that you can finde. For are any more holy then the great Patriarks were? And from ſome of Gods elect in al times great offences haue broken forth: take heede that for ſome ſuch particular faultes we iudge them not as men reiected of God, or ouer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely iudge them wicked and vngodly. And
<pb facs="tcp:18261:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> on the other part, you ſhall ſee the very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Goſpell, ſundrie of them which make a goodly ſhew in outward deedes, they bee prophane as <hi>Eſau,</hi> and all the ſhew of their workes is nothing before God.</p>
            <p>Well, now to the ſeuerity of Gods wrath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Eſau,</hi> for that is the principall matter which we haue in hand. He vvas reiected, hee found no place for repentance, though hee ſought it with teares. What is this? <hi>Eſau</hi> had the repulſe, when he came and vvould haue inherited the bleſſing: and then ſeeking euen vvith teares to obtaine it, <hi>Iſaake</hi> could not bee moued to alter that which he had done, there was no place to repent him, and ſo to call it backe againe from <hi>Iaakob,</hi> who had got it by ſleight. For now was <hi>Iſaake</hi> ſtricken with an exceeding feare, and euen as it were, awaked out of the error of his natural affection; and ſaw that the thing came of God: for that <hi>Iſaake</hi> cannot alter the thing he had done, nor repente, it proceedeth from God. Marke then the ſeueritie of God: <hi>Eſau</hi> had ſet light by the birthright, ſo prophane he was, that he loued the life preſent more: yet when he doth conſider of it more aduiſedlie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> iudgeth it to be a great thing, and wiſheth ſo earneſtlie to haue it, that when he ſaw it taken from him, he cried out bitterlie and wept, but his crying and his teares doe not moue God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18261:54"/> ſhew anie pittie or compaſſion towardes him. Therein now lieth the matter. For God laide a great terror vpon <hi>Iſaake,</hi> and held his minde, that although he loued <hi>Eſau</hi> dearely, yet he ſaw now, that he might not giue the bleſſing vnto him. What was there in all the world which <hi>Iſaake</hi> loued ſo tenderly as hee loued his ſonne <hi>Eſau.</hi> How can it be then, but he muſt needes be moued much with the dolefull crie that hee vttered, and with thoſe teares that hee ſhed? Why was not his wrath kindled againſt <hi>Iaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kob?</hi> Why did he not call for him, and tell him that as he had no meaning to bleſſe him, ſo he would now reuoke it, and beſtowe the ſame where he did purpoſe, yea, and thought he had beſtowed it? All men may eaſily perceiue, that this did proceede from the ſeueritie of Gods diſpleaſure. <hi>Iſaak</hi> like an holy man, &amp; as a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father had carefully inſtructed his ſonnes in the couenant, &amp; ſhewed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable treaſures of felicitie were included there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>Iaakobs</hi> minde was inflamed with a burning deſire thereof, but <hi>Eſau,</hi> though he vnderſtood the doctrine, yet ſet little by it, and that is the cauſe why God was ſo angrie with him. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſhall thinke, was this ſo great a cauſe to moue the Lorde ſo to wrath, that he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forgiue him? Iudge of it thus. If a prince offer vnto a ſubiect great honour, and it bee
<pb facs="tcp:18261:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſpiſed, will it not be hardlie taken? Now, when the king of kings dooth ſet before miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinfull men the high dignitie, glorie, and felicitie, euen to become his ſonnes and heires with Chriſt of the eternall kingdome, and they eſteeme baſelie thereof, how can he but be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly diſpleaſed at ſuch a prophane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt? Let vs not then maruaile that this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane man is reiected, but rather take heede to our ſelues leaſt we be like him, and ſo be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of God as he was. If he cried and wept and could not be heard, ſurely, if wee take not heede, we may ſo highlie offend, that when we crie and weepe, we ſhall not be heard. There can no heauier iudgement of God light vpon a man then this. The ſumme (as it were a botom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe gulfe of al miſeries &amp; plagues) is contained in it: as when a man ſhal cal and crie out bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with teares for the bleſſing of God, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of life eternall, and be reiected. Here is a pitte to fall into, heere is a daunger vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerable, yea heere is a ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which may make vs all to tremble and quake to come nigh it. For if men will quake when they looke downe from the toppe of an high tower to the ground. If when there is daunger of falling: how much more are we to feare at this? There a man may fall ſo high, that he daſhe in peeces vpon the ground, and ſo be
<pb facs="tcp:18261:55"/> depriued of this natural life: but here is the loſſe of life eternall, and that with the ſuſtaining of endles ſorrowes. It may be ſome will take it to be an hard collection, to gather from this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Eſau:</hi> who cried to his father with b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cryings to haue the bleſſing: and alſo ſought it with teares, and was reiected, that therefore men may call and crie to God, and euen with ſobbing &amp; teares craue pardon of their ſinnes, and yet not be heard. <hi>Eſau</hi> did not pray to God but ſought the bleſſing at the handes of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and ſhall a generall doctrine be drawne from a particular example? I haue ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the reiecting came from God: farre was it from the naturall affection of <hi>Iſaake</hi> ſo to haue reiected <hi>Eſau,</hi> if it had bene in his own power. Alſo, we may ſee that the holy ghoſt doth propound this example in one man for a generall doctrine: euen this, that ſuch men as like <hi>Eſau</hi> prophanely diſpiſe the graces of God ſhall afterward crie bitterlie and weepe, and call for the bleſſing of God, and yet bee reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of him. And to ſpeake the trueth, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde of God doth teach vs this onelie by the example of <hi>Eſau:</hi> but deliuereth it forth in flatte and plaine tearmes, as a generall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. In the firſt Chapter of the <hi>Prouerbes, Salomon</hi> bringeth in wiſedome, preaching, and calling vpon men to receiue her inſtruction.
<pb facs="tcp:18261:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> And then ſhee complaineth that they diſpiſe her counſell, &amp; ſo vttereth a terrible threatning, that ſhee will laugh at their deſtruction, and mocke when their feare commeth. She ſaith, they ſhall call vpon her, but ſhee will not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, they ſhall ſeeke her earlie, but ſhall not f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de her. With many moe ſpeeches there this matter is ſet forth. Chriſt is that wiſedome of the father, which calleth there vnto men, to returne vnto him, to imbrace his lawes and holy doctrine, offering all ſpirituall bleſſings in heauenlie thinges: but men ſet light by his counſell, they be addicted to the worlde, &amp; to the vaine pleaſures of ſinne, &amp; ſo with profane mindes diſpiſe the heauenly giftes and graces, This doth moue his indignation ſo farre, that he ſaith, he will be ſo farre from pittying them is their calamitie, that he wil laugh at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and mocke them in their feare and diſtreſſe. Yea, he ſheweth plainelie that they will call vpon him for helpe, but hee will not anſwere, they ſhall alſo earlie ſeeke him, but not finde him.</p>
            <p>Can any thing be more plaine then this? do you not marke the reaſon? Such as will not heare the Lord calling ſo earneſtly to them, &amp; offring ſo great kindnes, he will not regard nor heare them, when in their diſtreſſe they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:18261:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> cry vnto him. In the <hi>28. chapter</hi> of the <hi>Prou. ver. 9.</hi> it is written, <hi>He that turneth away his ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hearing the lawe, euen his prayer ſhall be abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Is not this a moſt fearefull thing? Is not thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame alſo in effect with that which is hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſpoken of <hi>Eſau.</hi> Then the doctrine is generall. Let euery man then take heed to it. God doeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now offer vnto vs grace, hee hath ſent vnto vs the word of reconciliation: he openeth vnto vs the heauens, &amp; calleth vs with an holy calling: then take heede wee be not ſo prophane, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o ſet light by it: for if we doe, it may be that we ſhall afterwardes ſeeke it with teares, and yet miſſe thereof. Men cannot beleeue this, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they liue diſſolutely, truſting that at their end they ſhall call to God for grace, and ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pardon. O poore wretches, if their prayer it ſelfe then be abominable, wher is their help? what ſhall become of them? I pray you le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> repeat it againe. The Lord God doth call vpon men to turne vnto him from their wicked and ſinfull wayes, he promiſeth to become their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as it is written in the Prophet, and allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Apoſtle, <hi>2. Cor. 6. ver. 17.18.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among them, ſaith the Lord, and ſeparate your ſelues, and touch no vnclea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing, and I will receiue you, and I wil be you father, and you ſhall be my ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſaith the Lord God almighty, and beeing
<pb facs="tcp:18261:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſonnes, they bee the heyres of God, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low heires with Chriſt, <hi>Rom. 8.</hi> Nowe, while this dignitie and glory is propounded and ſet before them, men prophanelie diſpiſe the ſame, they doe more eſteeme a meſſe of pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, they ſatisfie their vaine luſtes and carnall appetites: they haue all threatnings in deriſion: they will repent and cal for grace, when age or ſicknes ſhall take holde of them: they hope to do euen as well then as the godlieſt of them all that liue vpon the earth. Thus with <hi>Eſau</hi> they fall to their pottage, what care they for the birth-right? Well, ſicknes comes, terror of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ariſeth from the ſight &amp; remembrance of their ſins in which they haue walked, they muſt now come before the high Iudge, they wiſh now that they had neuer committed ſuch abominable and filthy vices: where is their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge? onely in prayer. They cry out with feare, with horror, and with teares. And where are they then: if this their prayer be abominable to God? Ye ſee the place which I alleaged, <hi>Prou. 28.</hi> Which telleth vs ſo. They crie and call now vnto Chriſt, and he doth mocke them, and laugh at their deſtruction, as he ſaith hee will, <hi>Prou. 1.</hi> Doe you not ſee now what a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full caſe theſe prophane men are in, which now diſpiſe the grace of God, that the prayer and the repentance which they truſt vnto is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.
<pb facs="tcp:18261:57"/> This is hard will ſome man ſay. For doe not they eſteeme highly of Gods bleſſings which weepe and crie to haue it? Againe doth not the Scripture teach that God will forgiue at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his ſinne? Shall we ſay that they doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent which crie with teares to GOD for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie? To this I anſwere, that <hi>Eſau</hi> woulde faine haue had the bleſsing at the laſt, but that doth not argue but that he was prophane. Who is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that woulde not willingly be ſaued? Or who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo prophane, but that he would bee glad to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape from the damnation of hell? And touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their crying with teares, it is not true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance no more then that in <hi>Eſau.</hi> He wep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not for any deteſtation of his prophaneſſe, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> becauſe he had loſt the bleſſing. Euen ſo theſe doe weepe and crie out, not that they loath and hate the ſinne, by which they haue diſhonoured GOD, and defiled themſelues, but becauſe their conſcience doeth terrifie them with the loſſe of heauen, and with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> feare and horror of hell. O beloued learne to knowe true repentance, leaſt we bee ſeduced and caried awrie to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>It will bee obiected further, that the holy Scriptures doe teſtifie, how ſome haue repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at their ende and haue beene ſaued: as for example the theefe vppon the croſſe. And
<pb facs="tcp:18261:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſt in the Parable of the man that hired la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into his Vineyarde, doeth teach that ſome come at the eleauenth hower. Moſt true it is, that God alwayes hath, and doth conuert ſome euen towarde the ende of their life, when as they haue ſpent a long time in wickedneſſe, for thereby the Lorde doth declare the riches of his mercie drawing men euen out of hell, which of themſelues would neuer haue retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But ſhall euerie man therefore preſume that God will doe the ſame to him? He doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the eyes of ſome, giuing them faith and repentance which haue liued in blindneſſe and ignoraunce al their life: will he therefore heare thee which haſt for a great part of thy life, yea it may bee euen from thine infancie, beene taught, and haſt diſpiſed the grace of GOD, boldning thy ſelfe in ſinfull wayes, and ſaying thou wilt cal for mercie and pardon at thine ende. Yea thou ſayeſt that thou haſt knowne many which haue liued verie wickedly, which haue made as good an ende as the godlieſt, calling euen to their laſt breath for mercie, and for pardon. Well <hi>Eſau,</hi> truſt not to ſuch kinde of repentance, thinke not that ſuch muſt needs be ſaued, becauſe they weepe and cry for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: but heare what Chriſt hath ſpoken, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> the ſeauenth. <hi>Not euerie one that ſayth vnto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome
<pb facs="tcp:18261:58"/> of heauen, but hee that doth the will of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is in heauen.</hi> Turne, turne, and doe the will of God while thou haſt time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> godly life, that ſo thou mayeſt ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a godly and a happie ende. Let vs call vpon God for this wiſedome and grace.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the third Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Romanes. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>1</bibl> What ſhall we ſaye then? ſhall we continue ſtill in ſin that grace may abound? God forbid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>2</bibl> How ſhall we that are dead to ſin yet liue therein?</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>3</bibl> Know yee not that all we which haue beene bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into Ieſus Christ, haue beene baptiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his death?</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>4</bibl> We are buried then with him by baptiſme into his death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed vp from the dead by the glorie of the Father, ſo we ſhould walke in newneſſe of life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>5</bibl> For if we bee grafted with him to the ſimilitude of his death, euen ſo ſhall we be to the ſimilitude of his reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>6</bibl> Knowing this, that our olde man is crucified with him, that the body of ſinne might bee deſtroyed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerue ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>7</bibl> For he that is dead is freed from ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>8</bibl> Wherefore if we be dead with Chriſt, we belieue that we ſhall alſo liue with him.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18261:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>9</bibl> Knowing that Chriſt being rayſed from the dead dieth no more, death hath no more dominion ouer him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>10</bibl> For in that he dyed, he dyed once to ſinne, but in that he liueth, he liueth to God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>11</bibl> Likewiſe thinke yee alſo, that yee are deade to ſinne, but are aliue to God in Ieſus Christ our Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>12</bibl> Let not ſinne raigne therefore in your mortall body that you ſhould obey it, in the luſtes thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>13</bibl> Neither giue yee your members as weapons of vnrighteouſneſſe vnto ſinne, but giue your ſelues vnto God, as they that are aliue from the deade, and giue your members as weapons of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>14</bibl> For ſinne ſhall not haue dominion ouer you, for yee are not vnder the law but vnder grace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former part of this Epiſtle, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 16. verſe of the firſt Chapter vnto the ende of the fift, <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath diſputed of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and now in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he entereth into a diſcourſe touching ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification. Theſe be two principall pointes of doctrine, moſt neceſſarie for all Chriſtians to
<pb facs="tcp:18261:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> be well inſtructed and grounded in. I ſuppoſe that ſome doe not vnderſtand the difference betweene iuſtification, and ſanctification: it is requiſite therfore that I touch that firſt. Chriſt, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Is our righteouſneſſe and our ſanctification 1. Cor. 1. ver. 30.</hi> Our righteouſnes, is our iuſtification: ſo that by that Scripture, it is euident that iuſtification and ſanctification be two ſeuerall things. In deede the Papiſtes doe confound them, or make them both one, while they make our ſanctification, or righteouſneſſe inhaerent, to be our iuſtification. To bee iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is to be made righteous from al guiltineſſe of ſinne, and ſo to be acquite and cleared from the curſe and penaltie thereof. To bee ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is to be drawne out of the yoke and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of ſinne and ſinfull luſtes, to the ſeruice of God in true holines. But this is not enough to make it cleare vnto euery mans vnderſtanding what the difference is betweene them: I muſt therefore ſpeake further in this matter. Firſt therefore concerning iuſtification, <hi>S. Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this Epiſtle, calleth it the righteouſneſſe of God, and ſaith, it is reuealed in the Goſpell from faith to faith, Chapter 1. verſe 17. And then ſheweth that all men both Iewes &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, are of themſelues grieuous ſinners, voide of righteouſneſſe. The true belieuers are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied or made righteous in Chriſt. So the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:18261:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> of God, is that righteouſneſſe which God giueth vnto vs in Chriſt, which is called the righteouſneſſe of faith, becauſe faith doeth apprehend it, Chapter 3. ver. 21.22? Wee may alſo ſay that it conſiſteth of two partes: the one is the free forgiueneſſe of ſins through Chriſtes bloud, euen of grace Chapter 3. ver. 24.25. For vntill there bee a ſatisfaction for ſinne, and ſo the guiltineſſe thereof purged away, there can be none iuſt before God. Then further the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part is this, wee are bounde to keepe the whole law, which we breake, and Chriſt in our nature hath perfectly fulfilled it, and his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is imputed to thoſe that do beleue in him: wherefore hee ſaith, as by one mans diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence many were made ſinners, ſo by the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of one ſhall many alſo bee made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Chapter 5. ver. 19.</p>
            <p>Thus may we ſee what iuſtification is, euen the purging away of all our ſins, and of all ſpot of ſinne by Chriſtes bloud: and the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his obedience in fulfilling the lawe. Thus al that belieue are made righteous in Chriſte. This is it which he writeth in another place, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he made him to be ſinne for vs, which knew no ſinne, that we in him might bee made the righteouſneſſe of God. <hi>2. Cor. 5. ver. 21.</hi> Then ſanctification is that which is called the newe birth, repentance, the putting off the old man,
<pb facs="tcp:18261:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the putting on the newe. The mortifying and putting off ſinne, and all ſinfull luſtes of the fleſh, &amp; the walking in the vertues of the ſpirit. This is alſo called righteouſnes, it is the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in Here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that doth ſtick in the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the righteouſneſſe which conſiſteth in the godly deedes of men. Of this, the holy Apoſtle in the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chapters diſputeth at large. And the ſumme of this matter is this, that iuſtification in Chriſt and ſanctification doe goe inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble together. There is no man which hath his ſinnes pardoned by the bloud of Chriſt, and that hath the obedience of Chriſt reckoned to be his: but he hath alſo the grace of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he hath vnfained repentance, he renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vice, and followeth vertue. Manie doe parte theſe two aſunder, for they doe verie wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie hearken to this, that Chriſt hath by his bloud, made ſatisfaction for our ſinnes, and that we in his obedience ſhall bee made righteous before God, this is comfortable: but when they heare that he hath redeemed vs, that wee ſhould denie our ſelues, forſake our ſinful luſts, and leade a godlie life according to the rules of his holy will, that is, ſower, and vnpleaſant. Let ſuch giue eare vnto <hi>S. Paul,</hi> for hee dooth by two arguments in this Chapter, which are drawen euen from two principles in reaſon, proue, that whoſoeuer is not ſanctified in Chriſt, he is not iuſtified in him, he may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb facs="tcp:18261:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> that his ſinnes ſhall be forgiuen him; but they ſhall not? a matter of verie great waight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> let vs then come vnto it. What ſhall wee ſay then (faith <hi>S. Paul</hi>) Shall wee continue ſtill in ſinne, that grace may abound? Here is the whole queſtion, here is the ſtate of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſe which is to be decided. The wordes of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are ſo plaine, that they neede no ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but onely in this, to ſee how this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is made, or dependeth vpon ſome matter vttred in the former Chapter. You may ſee there, how the Apoſtle at the 12. verſe, entreth into a compariſon betweene <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which are as two ſtockes, or fountaines: from the one, that is from <hi>Adam,</hi> there hath ſprung and flowed ſinne and death ouer all men: from the other, that is Chriſt, there ſpringeth, and floweth righteouſneſſe and life. Herein they be like, that both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe make thoſe which are theirs, partakers of that which they haue. But herein they be vnlike, that <hi>Adam</hi> deriueth ſinne, and that vnto death, into all them that are his, euen into all his poſteritie, by nature, or by a naturall propagation, for they haue all ſinned in him: Chriſt beſtoweth his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon thoſe which be his vnto life eternal, by grace, by a free gift, they haue it not as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> children haue their ſinne from him by a naturall ſpreading, but by imputation? Alſo, there be other differences: as namelie, all are
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:18261:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> made guiltie, and caſt downe by one offence of <hi>Adam:</hi> but Chriſt by his righteouſneſſe free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen vnto vs, doth not onely abſolue vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that one offcnee, but from all other ſinnes, which we haue committed. And the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſte imputed by grace, is of greater power to ſaue vs, then the ſinne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne vs. Seeing then, that as by the diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Adam,</hi> many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of Chriſt, many are made righteous. Why came the lawe? To this <hi>Saint Paul</hi> anſwereth, that the lawe entred, that ſinne might abounde, but where ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, there grace hath ſuperabounded. The greater the ſinne was, the more plenteous was the grace of God in Chriſt, in taking it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. That as ſinne had raigned vnto death, ſo grace ſhould raigne through righteouſnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life eternall, by Ieſus Chriſt: Then the more that ſinne abounded, the greater is the riches of the grace of God in Chriſt that doth pardon it, and ſo the greater is the praiſe and glorie of God. All this is true. Now hereupon the wiſedome of the fleſh doth argue thus. If the more the ſinne be increaſed, the greater is the glorie of God in pardoning it, then is it good for thoſe which beleeue in Chriſte to continue ſtill in ſinne, to commit all abundance of ſinne, that ſo God may haue the greater glorie.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:18261:62"/>
            <p>This is a pleaſant doctrine to mans corrupt nature, and much followed in all places: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit you ſhall not heare many vſe the ſame words which <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſetteth downe, to bolden themſelues to continue in ſinne: yet marke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well, and you ſhall perceiue that there is the ſame reaſon in effect. Great multitudes, as you knowe, doe profeſſe Chriſt, and they ſay, they looke to haue all their ſinnes forgiuen, only be his death and bloudſhedding. Look vpon then liues, and you ſhall finde that the greateſt pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouerwhelmed, and lie as it were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in all manner of vncleane and abominable vices. Deale particularly with any one, and ſay but thus vnto him, Theſe foule ſinnes which you continue in and daylie commit, are ſuch as God doeth threaten vengeance againſt: will he not anſwere? I know they be grieuous ſins, but I hope to haue them al forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me through the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt: yea, are there not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which will ſay, I hope I ſhall call for mercie and pardon at the laſt? This is the doctrine of the holy Ghoſt, the grace of God which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſaluation, hath appeared vnto all men, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs to denie vngodlines &amp; worldly luſtes, and to liue ſoberly, iuſtly and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, <hi>Tit. 2. ver. 11.12.</hi> Behold how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the doctrine of GOD ſuch men be. He ſaith that the grace giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in Chriſt, doth teach
<pb facs="tcp:18261:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> vs to deny all wicked waies, and to liue a godly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fer and they ſay, becauſe there is pardon in Chriſt, we will continue ſtill in our wickednes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all for mercy at the laſt. Al ſuch men doth the holy Apoſtle heere quite cut downe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>g indeed that they haue no part in Chriſt, they doe but deceiue themſelues. Alſo he doth heere meete with the Papiſtes, which are eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the croſſe of Chriſt, and can by no meanes indure to heare that we haue our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication only in Chriſt: but they will haue mens owne good works and merites to iuſtifie them before God. And thus they cry out againſt vs: you open a gappe vnto all looſenes and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſnes of life, you deſtroy all zeale and care of good works, when you teach that men are iuſtified onely by faith in Chriſt: for if a man ſhall haue all his ſinnes forgiuen by the grace of Chriſt, what wil he eare what ſinnes he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit? Alſo if a man ſhall be made righteous on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by grace in Chriſt, and not by his own good deedes, who will care to doe anie? This alſo I ſay, doth <hi>S. Paul</hi> here meete withal, ſhewing and proouing by ſtrong reaſons, that all they which haue a true faith in Chriſt, and ſo haue al their ſinnes forgiuen by his bloude, and haue alſo his obedience imputed vnto them, and be fully iuſtified, cannot but liue a godly life. Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in Chriſt and true ſanctification can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:18261:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> be parted aſunder: firſt therefore propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the queſtion, <hi>Shall we continue ſtill in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that grace may abound?</hi> he reiecteth it with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, ſaying, <hi>God forbid:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, It is a thinge that ought not to enter into our thoughts. And then he propoundeth the firſt reaſon, in theſe words, <hi>How ſhall we that are dead to ſinne yet liue therein?</hi> This is a principle in the light of natural reaſon, ſo that if a man haue not loſt the common vnderſtanding, he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it. We all doe know that contraries cannot be together in the ſame ſubiect, at one time, in the ſame part, and in the ſame reſpect, but the one neceſſarily doth exclude the other, and if the one be, it is vnpoſſible that the other ſhould alſo be. And that is the cauſe why <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>How can we which are dead to ſinne, yet liue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</hi> As much as to ſay, it is vnpoſſible: for to be aliue to ſinne, and to be dead to ſinne, at the ſame time (which are ſo flat and perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries) cannot be. He that is aliue is not dead, and he that is dead is not aliue. Thus now the matter ſtandeth: wee, that is all true Chriſtians, are dead to ſinne, howe can wee then liue to ſinne? And ſo if it bee vnpoſſible for a man which is a right Chriſtian, and therefore dead to ſinne, yet to liue in it, how ſhould wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill in ſinne that grace may abounde? Well, may ſome man ſay, This is a cleare caſe,
<pb facs="tcp:18261:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> that ſuch contraries as theſe, to be aliue and to be dead, cannot ſtand together: but how ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> appeare, that a true Chriſtian of neceſſitie is dead to ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>S. Paule</hi> hath but affirmed that we are de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to ſinne: and therefore in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> words he proueth it: for the death to ſinne being proued, the life to ſinne is thereby of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity excluded. <hi>Knowe ye not</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that all wee which haue beene baptized into Ieſus Christ, haue beene baptized into his death?</hi> Loe heere is his proofe: and this is a plaine, a ſtrong and an inuincible demonſtration, that euery true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is deade to ſinne, and ſo by conſequence cannot poſſibly be aliue to ſinne. It is drawen from the vſe of Baptiſme, or from that which Baptiſme doth repreſent vnto vs. It repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that we are ingrafted into Chriſt, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, Knowe you not that wee which haue bene baptized into Ieſus Chriſt? Beeing then baptized into Chriſt, the holie Baptiſme doth repreſent vnto vs that wee are waſhed in his bloude, and ſo haue the free remiſsion of our ſins, but alſo that in him wee haue the new, the ſpirituall and the heauenly birth. Now the death of Chriſt is as it were the fountaine of this regeneration: &amp; therefore the Apoſtle put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in minde that wee are baptized into the death of Chriſt. He that is baptized muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that hee is baptized into Chriſt crucified, and therefore into the death of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18261:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>To what end then, was the death of Chriſt? Not onely to make ſatisfaction for ſinnes but alſo to deſtroy, and vtterly to aboliſh ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nne in his miſtical bodie, which is the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verſe 8.</hi> Sinne there; is called the workes of the deuill, which the ſonne of God was made manifeſt to looſe; that is, to diſſolue, to breake and ſo vtterly to deſtroy. Marke well then Chriſt died to ſlay ſinne: hee had none of his owne to ſlay: And thereupon it muſt needes follow, that his death, is to ſlay the ſinnes of thoſe which be ingrafted into him. This is it that <hi>Saint Paule</hi> ſayth, wee are baptized into his death, that is, wee are baptized into Chriſt crucified, that the power of his death may be in vs, to crucifie, and to ſlay our ſinne. He the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that hath not the bare ſigne alone in baptiſme, but the very efficacie of the grace repreſented, muſt needes, without all controuerſie be dead vnto ſinne. And therefore <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth inſinuate how groſly blind they are, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the principles of the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religion, in the doctrine of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, which ſuppoſe that a man can be a true Chriſtian, and yet continue in ſinne. Do ye not know (ſaith he) as if he ſhould ſay, It is a ſtrange thing, if ye knowe not this, that all which haue bene baptized into Chriſt Ieſus, haue bene baptized into his death? Know ye not that they which doe die with Chriſt, doe die vnto ſinne?
<pb facs="tcp:18261:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> how then can they liue vnto ſinne? or how can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be a true Chriſtian that continueth ſtill in ſinne <hi>S. Paule</hi> (as I ſaid) did propound this as a ſtrange matter, that any ſhould be found ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and blind, as not to know that all which are baptiſed into Chriſt Ieſus, are baptized into his death, and ſo haue ſinne ſlaine in them, are become dead to ſinne, and therefore cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer liue therein. But in our dayes it is no wonder: for the moſt which glory in their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, vnderſtand as much as a blocke, what the doctrine of Baptiſme is: for if they did, would they continue ſtill in ſo many wicked &amp; abominable vices, and yet imagine that they be true Chriſtians? What know they that euery true Chriſtian is baptized into the death of Chriſt, and that the power of his death is to ſlay ſinne in them? Can they be both aliue to ſinne, and dead to ſinne?</p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee that the firſt argument of the Apoſtle, but he doth open it more at large in the wordes that follow, becauſe it is ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a matter for all men to be well taught and inſtructed in. It is the new birth figured by baptiſme, of which the Apoſtle maketh three partes, the one from the death of Chriſt, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from his buriall, the thirde from his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. We are buried with him by Baptiſme, ſaith hee, into his death, that like as Chriſt was
<pb facs="tcp:18261:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> raiſed vp from the dead by the glory of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo we ſhuld walk in newnes of life: you ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it plainely here expreſſed, that in our baptiſme theſe three things are repreſented, namely, that we die with Chriſt, that wee are buried with Chriſt, and that wee riſe with Chriſt. Howe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this to be taken? Thus. The death of Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which we are baptiſed doth ſlay ſinne, which is called our olde man: this is the firſt ſtep, for vntill ſinne be ſlaine in vs, we can not liue vnto righteouſneſſe. And there is nothing of power to kill ſinne, but the death of Chriſt. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſteppe is buriall, for when a body is dead, it doth by little and little rotte and conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the graue. Euen ſo our olde man or ſinne, hauing receiued a deadly wound by the death of Chriſt, remaineth ſtill as a deade car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe in thoſe which bee in Chriſt, and by the vertue of Chriſtes buriall, doth euen as it were by little &amp; little too, rotte and conſume. This is certaine, that whoſoeuer is in Chriſt crucified, and ſo the power of Chriſts death in him, ſinne is ſlaine in him: yet ſinne is not by and by vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſhed, but remaineth in him, and by the vertue of Chriſts buriall is conſumed. Wee may not think then that ſo ſoone as euer a man is in Chriſt, that ſin is vtterly aboliſhed in him: but in continuance of time it diminiſheth and doth become leſſe and leſſe. What then if a
<pb facs="tcp:18261:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> man haue ſinne as ſtrong in him this yeare, as he had the laſt yeare, &amp; the laſt yeare as ſtrong as ten yeares paſt? Will not any man ſaye, that the burial of Chriſt hath not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> effect in him? Shal a dead body being buried, rotte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume nothing at all in ſo long time? Wel if ther be no power of his burial, there hath beene no power of his death, the body of ſinne is ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue and not ſlaine, for a body doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſo long as it is aliue. If it laſt, ſurely it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, and thereby we may bee ſure that hee in whome ſinne is not diminiſhed, is not partaker of the buriall of Chriſt, and then is hee alſo not partaker of his death, for they goe inſeperably together: wherefore <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him by baptiſme into his death.</hi> Such a man then as doth continue in ſinne, hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued onely the outward ſigne in baptiſme, but not the power of Chriſt crucified. Let all men beware of this, for if they haue but the external ſigne, that they are buried with Chriſt by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme into his death, and the power of his death and buriall, be not in them to ſlay and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the body of ſinne, they be as far off from the benefites of Chriſt, as either Iew or Turke. And now touching the third part of our newe birth, which is the walking in newneſſe of life: this followeth from the reſurrection of Chriſt.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:18261:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> As Chriſt (ſaith hee) was rayſed vp from the dead by the glory of the father, ſo wee ſhould walke in newnes of life. Heere needeth ſome expoſition to make this plaine. When he ſaith <hi>Chriſt was rayſed from the dead by the glorie of the Father,</hi> we may take it that the glorious power of God did rayſe him vp, and that GOD was grorified by his reſurrection, all which is true: but not the thing which <hi>S. Paul</hi> here meaneth, The Greeke prepoſition which is tranſlated (by) may (as it is ſometimes vſed) be tranſlated into, or vnto.</p>
            <p>Thus it is, Chriſt before his paſſion tooke vpon him the ſhape of a ſeruant, hauing as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>Phil. 2.</hi> Emptied himſelfe of the high glorie, being in the ſhape of GOD, when hee thought it no robberie to be equall with God: and then hee had taken vpon him all our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, ſinne onely excepted. Hee was ſubiect vnto hunger, to thirſt, to wearineſſe, and ſuch like. But when he roſe from the dead, all theſe things are left behinde, and he entreth into the glorie of the father, euen into the glorious and heauenly life of the Father: and we being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into him, and dying with him, muſt needs alſo bee rayſed vp with him into that heauenly life of God, which hee expreſſeth, by walking in newneſſe of life. Thus it is, if Chriſt dyed for
<pb facs="tcp:18261:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> to ſlay ſinne, and then roaſe vp from the deade into that heauenly and glorious life, then wee that die to ſinne with him, muſt needes be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp alſo with him, into the partaking of that ſpirituall and heauenly life. As the killing and burying of ſinne is called the putting off the olde man, ſo this riſing with Chriſt vnto new of life, is called the putting on of the new man. This is to walke in true holynes. Seeing all this is thus, I pray you how can hee be a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that doth continue in ſinne? Shall wee continue ſtill in ſinne, that grace may abound? You ſee it manifeſt, that a true Chriſtian is ſo farre off from continuing in ſinne, that contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe he doth walke in newneſſe of life. This <hi>Saint Paul</hi> doth further examplifie in the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that follow, namelie, that all they which die with Chriſt vnto ſinne, muſt needes alſo riſe with him vnto the partaking of the newe life, and further, that being once raiſed vp from the death of ſinne into that life of righteouſnes, they neuer returne backe againe to liue vnto ſinne. Touching the former of theſe, for to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, hee vſeth a ſimilitude taken from a plant. If (ſaith he) we be grafted to the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of his death, euen ſo ſhall wee be to the ſimilitude of his reſurrection? Thus it is, in the naturall plant, as we alſo doe knowe, that when
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:18261:67"/> the ſiences are grafted into a ſtocke, and that is digged into the ground, if the ſtocke die, they die with it, and if the ſtocke doe growe and ſpring vp, they doe growe and ſpring vp with it. Euen ſo, the holie Apoſtle teacheth, that a man being by faith grafted into Chriſt, as he is grafted, and doth grow to him by a myſticall and ſpirituall vnion to die with him, that is, as Chriſt died to ſlay ſinne, ſo he dyeth to ſinne, or ſinne by the power of Chriſtes death is ſlain in him: likewiſe, he is grafted vnto the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his reſurrection? that is, he receiueth the ſappe of life from Chriſt, as from the ſtocke into which he is grafted, and ſo doth liue and grow vp by him. Then you ſee by the doctrine of the holy Apoſtle, that from the neere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction which the faithfull haue with Chriſt, theſe two thinges goe inſeperablie together, the dying to ſinne, and the riſing to the newe life, euen the life of righteouſneſſe. For how ſhould a man be in Chriſt, and ſeperate theſe? As a man cannot haue iuſtification except hee be in Chriſt Ieſus: and if he be in him, he muſt needes with it bee partaker of the grace and power of ſanctification: ſo alſo, if he be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the one parte of ſanctification, he can not be voide of the other. If he be dead and buried with Chriſt, he ſhall alſo riſe with him.
<pb facs="tcp:18261:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> Whereby this is manifeſt, that where holie life appeareth not in a man, there ſinne is not ſlaine: for where there is a death and a buriall of ſinne, there muſt needes be a reſurrection vnto a new life. All they then are in the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of their ſinnes: which are not by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt quickned vnto a new life, euen to walke in the vertues of him that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs. What ſhall wee ſay vnto thoſe alſo which will ſeeme to haue the latter without the former? They would ſeeme to be verie riche and plenteous in good workes, and ſo to liue vnto righteouſneſſe: but looke vpon their life, and examine it by the rules of the holie worde of God, and you ſhall behodle great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous vices that raigne in them. As thoſe other which make no ſhewe of good workes, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrie when they imagine that they haue parte in the death of Chriſt, and yet they are not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his reſurrection, becauſe they haue no holy life: ſo theſe are vtterly deceiued which will ſeeme to be riſen with Chriſt vnto an holie life, and yet were neuer dead and buryed with him. In deede they cannot be raiſed vnto the life of righteouſneſſe, vnleſſe they haue firſt died vnto ſinne. Will they be grafted to the ſimilitude of Chriſtes reſurrection, and haue not bene grafted with him to the ſimilitude of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:18261:68"/> his death? What then are all thoſe good workes which they worke, that together, with thoſe good workes, doe mingle ſo many bad vices all their life long? Surely, their good deedes are euen ſuch, as the almes, faſting, and prayers of the Phariſies which Chriſt doth reproue, <hi>Mat. 6.</hi> Take this for a moſt vndoubted truth, that there is no holy life, but from the vertue of Chriſts reſurrection. There is no partaking of the true life of God, and conſequently not of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny action of that true life, but from hence, that a man be grafted with Chriſt to the ſimilitude of his reſurrection. And therefore all the good deeds which men doe, that haue not ſin firſt ſlaine in them, proceed but of vain-glory, ſelfe-loue, or from other ſuch ſiniſter reſpects. What is it when a prophane diſpiſer of Gods word, an horrible abuſer of Gods name, by ſwearing, a couetous, a proude and an hawty perſon, or an idolater, doth almes deeds? The poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede are relieued by it, but they doe not any thing that is good before God. And now tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the words that follow, <hi>Knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him, that the body of ſinne might be deſtroyed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerue ſinne, for he that is dead is freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being ſo notable a matter touching our ingrafting into Chriſt, and growing together
<pb facs="tcp:18261:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> with him to the ſimilitude of his death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the Apoſtle doth yet lay it open fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to that other pointe which I noted, of not returning backe again from the life of righteouſnes, to liue vnto ſin. But heere now the ſpeeches which are vſed be very effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall to expreſſe &amp; to open vnto vs this whole matter. As the olde man, crucified, the bodie of ſinne aboliſhed, and the ſeruice of ſinne from which we are freed. Firſt, what is it which hee calleth our old man? This you muſt vnderſtand, or elſe you ſhall not attaine to the doctrine of the Apoſtle. It is neyther the eſſence of our ſoule nor body, which is called the old man: but the corrupt qualities. As alſo the new man is in the pure &amp; vncorrupted qualities: as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are willed to put off the old man, and to put on the new man: it is a ſpeech borrowed from the putting off and on of garments: for the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the old man, is as the putting off a moſt filthy garment: the putting on the new man, is as the putting on of a pure and clean garment. Then further we muſt note, why it is called a man, our old man: and that is becauſe the filthy corruption hath by nature ouerſpread all parts of man, both within and without. All the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and faculties of the ſoule, and all the partes of the body are defiled: ſo that there is nothing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:18261:69"/> pure in man, as he is in himſelfe by nature. The power and dominion of ſinne hath gotten the maſtery ouer all that is in man. For this cauſe alſo, euen as the naturall body of man hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe members, ſo there are aſcribed members to the old man, as when he ſaith, <hi>Mortifie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your earthly members, Coloſ. 3.</hi> And then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coneth vp particularly thoſe members of the old man, euen vnclean vices, as you may reade in that Chap. Then he ſaith, <hi>Knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him.</hi> Here the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the death is noted, by which this our old corruption of ſinne is ſlaine, teaching withall that it is not crucified, but in the croſſe of Chriſt: for he ſaith, <hi>With him.</hi> This our old man will retaine his force and power vntill hee be ſlaine: it is not in man to come out of the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of his natiue corruption, vntil it be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to death; and nothing there is that can giue that deadly ſtroke vnto it, but onely the death of Chriſt: wherfore it is ſaid to be crucified with him. When a man is in Chriſt, and ſo the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of Chriſts death hath crucified his old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet there is ſtill a body of ſinne, there doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine that whole dead carkaſſe, though not with the force and dominion it had before, which daylie by little and little is conſumed &amp; aboliſhed: for ſo the words of the Apoſtle are,
<pb facs="tcp:18261:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> that the body of ſinne might be deſtroyed. Firſt the old man is crucified, that ſo the body of ſin may be deſtroyed. Behold here what is wroght by the redeemer. Sinne in mans nature may be eſpied, and many goodly precepts may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt it, with perſwaſions to come out of it, but all in vaine, vntill it be crucified with Chriſt. Moreouer, this we are to note, that the ſlaine body of ſinne, though through the burial of chriſt it do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume &amp; is diminiſhed in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, ſo that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to day the remna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of ſin haue leſſe &amp; leſſe force in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in them, &amp; none are fully deliuered from it ſo long as they liue in this world: for you may reade what the great Apoſtle cryeth out tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching himſelfe, <hi>O wretched man that I am! who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death? Rom. 7.24.</hi> This ſlaine body of ſinne doth ſtill annoy al the faithfull (but as he giueth thanks there) we ſhal bee fully deliuered by Chriſt Ieſus our Lord. Nowe followeth the end why our old man is crucified, namely, that henceforth wee ſhould not ſerue ſin. By nature we are all in bondage, wee are vnder a moſt tyrannous Lord that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ouer vs, euen ſin: wee doe our ſeruice and obedience thereto: Chriſt doth ſet vs free from this bondage (as he ſaith, <hi>If the ſonne make you free, then are you free indeede. Iohn, 8.</hi>) and it is by
<pb facs="tcp:18261:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſlaying the tyrant: wherefore he ſaith, <hi>He that is dead is free from ſinne.</hi> Wee all knowe this, that death ſetteth the bond ſeruant free from his maſter. Here-upon <hi>S. Paule</hi> doth reaſon, that if we be dead with Chriſt vnto ſinne, then are we freed from it. So that you may plainely ſee, that they that doe in ſuch ſort profeſſe the Goſpell of Chriſt, as that they doe continue ſtill in ſin, are little acquainted with this, that Chriſt came to ſlay ſin, that wee by dying there-unto, might be ſet free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſeruice and bondage thereof. And now to the other point, which is, that hee which is once crucified with Chriſt &amp; ſo is ded to ſin, the ſame muſt needs, as we ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, riſe with him, &amp; liue with him: wherevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it followeth, that he which ſo hath died &amp; riſen with Chriſt, can neuer returne againe vnto the ſpiritual death, which is to liue to ſin. This point is not common, I meane, euery one doth not vnderſtand it, and therefore I doe pray you to marke well the ſpeeches of the holy Apoſtle. Wherefore if we be dead with Chriſt, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that we ſhal alſo liue with him. This hath a neceſſary conſequence, as you haue ſeene before in the ſimilitude of a plant: where the ſcience grafted in growing to the ſtocke doeth die and liue with it. <hi>If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be dead with Chriſt vnto ſinne.</hi> If the power of his death hath cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:18261:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> our old man: then doe we beleeue that we alſo riſe with him vnto the new life: for hee ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vp to life, how ſhould we being pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and growing vnto him, but riſe alſo to life with him? This is the firſt ſtep vnto the matter now in hand. Then in the next place he addeth, that Chriſt being enrred into that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly life, neuer returneth out of it, to die anie more. This is ſo euident that he ſaith, <hi>Knowing that Chriſt beeing raiſed from the deade dieth no more, death hath no more dominion ouer him.</hi> If death haue no more dominion ouer him then can he neuer returne from that glorious life: for life is not taken away but by death. Nowe that death ſhall haue no more dominion ouer him, he ſheweth by this reaſon, that, in that he dyed, he dyed once to ſinne, but in that he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, he lyueth to God. This was the cauſe why Chriſt dyed, euen that he might ſatisfie for the ſinne of the world, and that he might deſtroye ſinne. This being once done, there is now no cauſe why it ſhould euer bee done againe, for the full ſatisfaction is made at once for euer, and ſinne by his croſſe ſhall bee vtterly diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But touching his life, the Apoſtle ſaith he liueth to God: his life then is perpetuall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting.</p>
            <p>Thus much touching Chriſt the head. And
<pb facs="tcp:18261:71"/> now hee commeth to the application of it in the members. Likewiſe thinke yee alſo that ye are dead to ſinne, but are aliue to GOD in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Firſt in theſe wordes the Apoſtle willeth vs, not barely (as the worde is tranſlated) to thinke: for that is but an opinion: but to conclude as it were neceſſarie by a Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme (for that ſpeech he vſeth) that wee are deade to ſinne and are aliue to God through Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>Here now lyeth the force of his matter, as Chriſt dyed but once for to ſatisfie for ſinne &amp; to ſlay it, ſo all the true members of Chriſt can but once die to ſinne. Sinne or the olde man being once crucified in them, and hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the deaths wound, can neuer reuiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Chriſt dyed once to ſinne, ſo his muſt die but once to ſin, for being in him can they be off and on, now dead to ſin, now aliue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it? Moſt true it is, that ſinne is in the faithfull by degrees put downe, and not at once: but yet it is at once by the death of Chriſt ſlaine. Then the partie in whome the old man is once crucified and ſlaine, is alſo ryſen with Chriſt and is partaker of the new life, and ſo with him, or rather in him, is aliue to God. Then marke the drift of the Apoſtle: If Chriſt could die but once to ſinne and then liueth for euer: then
<pb facs="tcp:18261:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> they that be in Chriſt can die but once to ſinne, and likewiſe doe liue with him to God for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. How then can the olde man once crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, euer recouer life againe? Or how can the new life, the life of God being once begun be vtterly extinct in any? Seeing the Apoſtle doth argue vpon this ground, that as Chriſt can not alter, ſo they that bee in Chriſt can not alter. How then ſhall they that bee in Chriſt, and ſo dead to ſinne yet liue therein? Howe can any true Chriſtian man continue in ſin, that grace may abound: but eſpecially conſider how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie they be vnto this place, which holde that a man may be regenerate in Chriſt, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall from it. By the doctrine of thoſe, the olde man may be crucified and ſlaine in a man, and liue againe, and ſo againe he may bee ſlaine (if they leaue place for repentance) and liue alſo from that. Alſo by their doctrine, the life of God may in a man be extinct, and ſo he doth not in Chriſt liue to God. Why then doth <hi>S. Paule</hi> here make ſuch a compariſon between Chriſt and his members which are grafted into him? But let theſe paſſe, and returne againe to the former. <hi>S. Paul</hi> now draweth from hence an exhortation vnto all Chriſtians, that ſeing their profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> figured by baptiſme, is ſo as they muſt die with Chriſt to ſinne, and riſe alſo with him
<pb facs="tcp:18261:72"/> vnto the new life, that therfore they would not let ſinne raigne in their mortal bodies &amp;c. If ſin be ſlaine in you, then you muſt not let it raigne in you, for is that meet, that a dead thing ſhould raigne? And ſhall men obey the luſtes of that which is ſlaine? Surely if ſinne raigne, ſinne is not ſlaine: if any man doe obey the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is aliue ſtill in him. Such a man without all controuerſie is not in Chriſt, but now marke how the bleſſed Apoſtle doeth frame his ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in this exhortation. He doth not ſay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, let not ſinne remaine at all in you, or ſee that in no wiſe you bee found to ſinne: for then all are loſt, if none be in Chriſt, if none bee dead and ryſen with him, but ſuch as are quite voide of all ſinne, <hi>But let not ſinne raigne in your mortall bodie.</hi> Here is all that the faithfull are called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for while they liue here, namely that they obey not the luſtes of ſinne, and ſo giue vnto it a kingdome and a dominion in them. He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth plainely by this that the ſlaine body of ſinne remaineth ſtill in them, and the luſtes thereof be in the minde, but wee muſt not obey them. Alſo he ſaith, <hi>Let it not raigne in your mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> What doth hee by this, giue alowance that ſinne may raigne in the mind. Surely that were a ſmall reformation, if ſinne ſhould bee reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely in our bodies, and retaine the full
<pb facs="tcp:18261:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> force ſtill in the mind. But ſeeing it can not be but that the motions of ſin wil ariſe in the mind he doth aduertiſe that yet wee ſhould reſtraine our bodies from performing thoſe luſts. It is the like ſpeech when <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be angrie but ſin not.</hi> Hee ſpeaketh not there of an holy anger, which indeede is not ſinne, for then he woulde not will vs to cut it off, ſaying, <hi>Let not the ſunne goe downe vpon your wrath,</hi> but he doth thereby inſinuate, that man is ſo prone vnto anger, and it doth ariſe ſo ſuddainely oftentimes euen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery occaſion that it can not bee auoided, neuertheleſſe, hee doth aduiſe that we ſhoulde not performe the cruell deedes which anger doth leade vnto. Seeing it can not bee, but that the filthie motions and luſtes of ſinne will ariſe in the minde, yet reſiſt them ſo (this is his councell) that they raigne not in your mortall bodies, or giue not vp your bodies in action to performe ſuch wicked motions. Labor to haue the minde wholy purged from them, but ſeing that can not bee fully attained, let them not haue the raigne and dominion in your bodies. And further, in this exhortation hee willeth vs, not to giue our members as weapons of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe vnto ſinne, but giue (ſaith he) your ſelues vnto GOD, as they that are aliue from the deade, and giue your members as
<pb facs="tcp:18261:73"/> weapons of righteouſneſſe to God. To vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this, you muſt conſider that the holye Ghoſt likneth ſinne vnto a mightie tyrant, who hath his miniſters and ſeruants, attending and ſetting themſelues in his preſence, to waite his pleaſure what ſeruice he wil commaund them, which then they execute. And therefore hee vſeth here the like phraſe of ſpeech, willing vs not to ſet our members in the preſence of ſin, as weapons, or inſtruments, or as it were mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters attending and ready to execute his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. This in deed is the miſerable bondage that man is in by nature, that all the powers and faculties of his ſoule, with all the members of his bodie, are euen willinglie preſt and readie, and doe euen preſent and ſet themſelues as at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants in the preſence of ſinne, readie to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the luſtes thereof. This being renounced, as it is reaſon, <hi>S. Paule</hi> exhorteth that we ſhould giue vp our ſelues to God, as they that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue from the dead, and our members as wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of righteouſneſſe. This is a goodlie thing which is here required: and all thinges conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered verie equall. We haue ſhewed our ſelues very ready to the obedience of ſinne, wee haue ſet all our members as attendant, to performe moſt willinglie the luſtes thereof. Shall we not now be as readie to giue vp our ſelues to God,
<pb facs="tcp:18261:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> being ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vp from the death of ſinne vnto the life of righteouſneſſe? and ſhall wee not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as willing to ſet all our members as mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and ſeruants to attend vpon righteouſnes, as we were to giue them to ſinne? Shal we not change our Lorde, if it be from the worſe to the better? Or ſhall wee not ſerue the better Lord as willing as we ſerued the worſe? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I pray you: what is the rewarde of thoſe which are the ſeruants of ſinne: Is it not eternal death, euen the torments of hell: and yet how chearefully men performe that ſeruice? Howe ready be they to obey the luſtes of ſinne? What is the reward of thoſe which ſerue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Is it not promiſed that they ſhall haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glorie, and ſhall we not then be as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and as ready to obey righteouſneſſe as we were to obey ſinne?</p>
            <p>And now to the laſt verſe, which I haue read vnto you, <hi>For ſin ſhall not haue dominion ouer you: for ye are not vnder the law, but vnder grace:</hi> This is a moſt excellent comfort, which <hi>S. Paule</hi> vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth to harten &amp; to encourage all the faithful to reſiſt ſinne. We heare of freedome from the yoke of our euill luſtes, wee are called vpon to renounce our obedience vnto ſinne. Alſo wee are willed to preſent all our members as wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of righteouſnes to God: but in the meane
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:18261:74"/> time we doe feele our ſelues ſo oppreſſed with the tyrannous power of ſin, that it ſeemeth we ſhall reſiſt in vaine. Yea it falleth out in manie, that the more they doe reſiſt, and ſtriue againſt their euill luſtes, the more furiouſly the ſame doe ſeeme to rage. Whereupon ſome doe giue ouer ſtriuing, feeling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo yoked, as that they thinke it vnpoſſible to winde out. For this cauſe <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sinne ſhall not haue do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> ouer you.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, be of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and faint not, reſiſt ſinne with all the force ye can: for albeit the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thereof do ariſe in you very ſtrong, and ſeeme often times euen to leade you away captiue, yet it ſhall not raigne Why may one ſay, doth not ſin raigne in you: where the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (which ariſeth in the minde) doth take place: ſo that a man is carried into ſome ſinfull actes? Surely we muſt iudge thus, that where a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth that which he vnfainedly hateth, and is drawen thereunto, euen againſt his will, he doth not obey ſinne, neither can it be ſaid that ſinne doth raigne in him: But is not ſuch a man in daunger that hee ſhall be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come? No verily, for marke what a reaſon the holy Apoſtle doth render. <hi>For yee are not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vnder the law, but vnder grace.</hi> The ſumme of the reaſon is this, ſinne hath loſt his force in you and is vnarmed, and you haue obtained an
<pb facs="tcp:18261:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> inuincible power againſt it, therefore goe on v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ntly in reſiſting, for you ſhal aſſuredly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the victorie, and ſinne ſhall not haue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ominion ouer you. Now ſinne hath loſt his force by this, that you are not vnder the lawe, and you haue obtained your power in this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are vnder grace. Is not this a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous encouragement? The tyrant is vtterly weakned, and you are mightily armed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goe to &amp; reſiſt, he ſhal not preuaile agianſt you. This you ſhall ſee plainely, if you did vnderſtand what it is not to be vnder the lawe, and what it is to be vnder grace. The lawe was Moral, Iudiciall, and ceremoniall. Here wee muſt needes take it of the lawe Morall: But now how is this to be vnderſtood, that he ſaith, we are not vnder the morall lawe? They bee vtterlie awrie which take it abſolutely, as if we had no more to doe with the lawe of GOD. The lawe is the rule of holy life: all vices are condemned onelie by it, and alone it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth all vertues: what then can be more abſurd, then that <hi>Saint Paul</hi> vrging godlie life, ſhould aboliſh the onely rule thereof? We are ſtil, vnder the lawe thus, to haue our minde, our will, our affections, our thoughtes, our wordes, and our deedes wholie framed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame. It is therefore but in ſome
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:18261:75"/> reſpecte, that <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaith, we are not vnder the lawe. Some doe take it to be meant, that we are not vnder the curſe of the lawe. Moſt true it is, that Chriſt hath deliuered his from the curſe of the lawe, as it is written, <hi>Gal. 3.</hi> but that appertaineth vnto iuſtification: <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth not here deale about iuſtification, but as we ſee plainely touching ſanctification, that is, the godlineſſe which is begun in all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Here then it muſt be vnderſtood ſo, as it is to be applied to the conflict that is betweene the fleſhe, and the ſpirite, in the regenerate. And that is thus, ye are not now vnder the lawe as it is the ſtrength of ſinne, <hi>1. Cor. 15.56.</hi> This matter is handled at large in the next Chapter, where he doth cleare the lawe from all blame, that it is the ſtrength of ſinne, or that the natiue corruption in vs, which as an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, hath force by the lawe in our members to bring forth children vnto death: that is, to beget, and to bring forth wicked deedes, in the faculties of our ſoules and bodies, being as the wife. For it is accidentarie to the lawe to doe this. For the lawe being ſpirituall, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring an heauenlie puritie, and lighting vpon our nature, which is carnall, or vtterlie corrupt, onely ſhewing our vncleanenes, and not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, concupiſcence becommeth more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb facs="tcp:18261:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> in vs, which without the lawe lyeth as it were dead. He that is in Chriſt, and ſo endewed with grace, or that is led by the ſpirit of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Which doth mortifie the deedes of the fleſhe, is not ſo vnder the lawe any longer, as that ſinne ſhould haue ſtrength thereby. Thus the holie Apoſtle then dooth encourage and comforte all thoſe that ſtriue to mortifie their ſinfull luſtes, telling them, that the tyrant hath loſt his force, which he had by the lawe in our corrupt nature, and that we are armed with the mightie power of grace to ſubdue him, and therefore, hee ſhall not haue dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs. What greater comfort then this? why ſhould we not take heart? The Lord increaſe his grace in vs, and make vs ſtrong in renouncing all obedience to ſinne, and in giuing vp our ſelues wholy to his ſeruice: Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
